<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to the frivolous and impertinent ansvver of R.B. to the discourse of P.B. In which discourse is shewed, that the baptisme in the defection of Antichrist, is the ordinance of God, notwithstanding the corruptions that attend the same, and that the baptisme of infants is lawfull, both which are vindicated from the exceptions of R.B. and further cleared by the same authour. There is also a reply, in way of answer to some exceptions of E.B. against the same.</title>
            <author>Barbon, Praisegod, 1596?-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B755</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E96_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5151</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872807</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872807</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78137)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 17:E96[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to the frivolous and impertinent ansvver of R.B. to the discourse of P.B. In which discourse is shewed, that the baptisme in the defection of Antichrist, is the ordinance of God, notwithstanding the corruptions that attend the same, and that the baptisme of infants is lawfull, both which are vindicated from the exceptions of R.B. and further cleared by the same authour. There is also a reply, in way of answer to some exceptions of E.B. against the same.</title>
                  <author>Barbon, Praisegod, 1596?-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to Barrow, Robert, A briefe answer to a discourse, and also to Edward Barber's A small treatise of baptisme, or, dipping.</note>
                  <note>Barrow's A briefe answer was in reply to Barebon's A discourse tending to prove the baptisme in or under the defection of Antichrist to be the ordinance of Jesus.</note>
                  <note>Epistle to the reader signed: R.B., by error for P.B. P.B. = Praisegod  Barbon. -- Cf. BLC.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill. 14.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Barrow, Robert, d. 1697. --  Briefe answer to A discourse lately written by one P.B. to prove baptisme under the defection of Antichrist.</term>
               <term>Barber, Edward, d. 1674? --  Small treatise of baptisme, or, dipping.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155820:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155820:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REPLY TO THE Frivolous and impertinent ANSVVER of <hi>R.</hi> B. to the diſcourſe of <hi>P.</hi> B.</p>
            <p>IN Which diſcourſe is ſhewed, that the Baptiſme in the defection of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> is the Ordinance of <hi>God,</hi> notwithſtanding the Corruptions that attend the ſame, and that the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of Infants is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, born which are vindicated from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of <hi>R. B.</hi> and further cleared by the ſame AUTHOUR.</p>
            <p>There is alſo a REPLY, in way of <hi>Anſwer</hi> to ſome Exceptions of <hi>E. B.</hi> againſt the ſame.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 IOHN 4. 1.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beleeve not every ſpirit, but trie the ſpirits whether they bee of</hi> GOD.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 THESS. 5. 21.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trie all things and keep that which is good.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the yeare 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:155820:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155820:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T commeth to paſſe often times, that words well ſpoken are by ſome ill taken, and matters clearely and plainely declared, are exceedingly wreſted and perverted, and the good intent of perſon who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubverted. It fared ſo of old with <hi>Moſes,</hi> with <hi>David,</hi> with <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> yea with our Lord himſelfe, and with all his holy Apoſtles in ſpeciall: it ſo fared with holy <hi>Paul,</hi> the great Teacher of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> there were ſome that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted his ſayings to their owne deſtruction; the holy Martyrs <note place="margin">Pet. 2. 3. 16.</note> and Confeſſors of the Truth, have had alſo experience of it in all Ages: all which conſidered I may not thinke it ſtrange, or count it a new thing, that it ſo fareth with mee, being one of the meaneſt of the ſervants of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and the rather for that I did looke for it, knowing I had to doe with perſons of froward and perverſe ſpirits, I indeavoured to make things plaine, ſo as I am checked for Tautologie by my oppoſite, I did indeavour with all Ingenuity to ſet forth the true meaning, and right grounds of my oppoſites judgement and practices, and then did make oppoſall by inferences and other poſitive arguments; I prayed them to meaſure ſuch meaſure to me in way of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; but contrarily they have fained Imaginary things, and
<pb facs="tcp:155820:3"/> fathered them on me with more lying falſhoods: and alſo ſo perverted the ſence and playne intent of my diſcourſe, as were it not for the taking off the falſhoods they have fathered on mee, and clearing of my diſcourſe, and the matter therein ſet forth, I ſhould count it needleſſe to ſpend time and paines in making reply to ſuch a lame and meane anſwer, I ſhould have l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft it to the judgement of the ſtudious <hi>Reader,</hi> whether he hath taken of the charge, and vindicated their judgement and practice from the errours and abſurdities by me obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted. Now courteous <hi>Reader,</hi> thou mayſt take notice, that ſince the publiſhing of that ſhort diſcourſe touching <hi>Baptiſme:</hi> ſome in their Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets have taken occaſion to carpe and ſnarle at ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars therein. But now on R. R. pretending great ſtrength in himſelfe, and weakneſſe in the diſcourſe, would ſeeme to make a full anſwer, and overthrow all, and which is more, foyle the Authour with his owne Weapons, and with one word of his mouth to blaſt the whole diſcourſe. But ſure if he be well minded, he will be found a vaine boaſter, and one that either not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood what he undertooke to anſwer: like to him that <hi>Solomon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 18. 13.</note> ſpeaketh of, that anſwereth a matter before he heare it, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he hath dealt malitiouſly, and unlike the ſervant of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> perverting the words, the ſcope and plaine meaning of his oppoſite, rather then confuting of him; toward the end of his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> he telleth his <hi>Reader,</hi> that not regarding to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his oppoſite to and fro, a fine ſhift to put off, or paſſe by that he could with no ſhew or Colour anſwer) he ſaith he will reduce the whole diſcourſe to three heads, the ſecond whereof hee ſaith is the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſure it is a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing, that he ſhould reduce a pare of my diſcourſe to ſuch a head (he dreamed certainly, for there is not one word, nor ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of it in all my diſcourſe, let him looke againe, and take ſpectacle to help his eyes, and he ſhall not find it, I treated in my diſcourſe of the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> under the defection of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> continuing <hi>Gods</hi> Ordinance, as Circumciſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb facs="tcp:155820:3"/> 
               <hi>Gods</hi> Ordinance under the defection of the ten Tribes; he hath a matter in his Imagination, and that hee putteth in the ſtead thereof; and it muſt be admitted to be the ſame, or elſe <hi>R. B.</hi> will thinke hee hath great wrong done him, though it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo contrary; if one had reaſoned to maintaine the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of the Apoſtate Tribes to have been the Ordinance of <hi>God,</hi> and ſome in oppoſition ſhould have intreated of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of the two Claves at <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethell,</hi> and ſhould be confident it is the ſame: <hi>Salomons</hi> ſaying would have bin made good, in ſuch a one as it is alſo in <hi>R. B.</hi> bray a foole in a morter, and his fooliſhneſſe will not leave him. I told him <note place="margin">Prov. 17. 22.</note> and made it plaine, ſo as he nor any other is able to gayneſay it, that corruption maketh not a nullity, which ſure he would have gayneſayed if he could, yet becauſe of the corruption, <hi>Baptiſme</hi> there muſt needs be an Idole, and his calling of it the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will make it ſo, and none ſhall help it for to tell him, otherwiſe he will ſay as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> did, how can it be as if hee or thoſe of his opinion had infallible know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and were able to comprehend all truth whatſoever, and what they doe not imbrace muſt needs bee an errour, and thoſe high ſinners that ſpeake or hold contrary, if <hi>R. B.</hi> did but minde his often changes he would not bee ſo high minded and confident, but would rather feare, hee was as confident of his firſt <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> certainly of his ſecond he was ſo, nothing might be ſpoken againſt them, but it was a great ſinne, and they high ſinners againſt the truth; yet he was miſtaken in his Iudgement in both, and they were Idolls in his account, and hee rejected them, and now this his third it is the onely truth, which none may ſpeake againſt, but he is a high ſinner, It were good for all men to beware of ſuch men according to <hi>Salomons</hi> Counſell: <hi>My Son fear God &amp;c. and meddle not with thoſe that are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 24. 21.</note> 
               <hi>given to change;</hi> a man that had a minde to come to <hi>R. B.</hi> in his third <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> before a yeare or two spent in the ſerious waighing of the matter, would find happily that <hi>R. B. had left</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:155820:4"/> his third <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and taken up afhurth, for by that time he could eſpie ſuch faultes in his former Baptiſme, and alſo in my diſcourſe, as to overthrow it by it ſelfe will, it is likely finde ſomething in his third <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> to make him reject that alſo. If hee bee true to his owne principle, he will finde ſome errour or corruption in it as in the former, that will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force him ſo to doe, I may tell him, and he and all other ſhall finde it ſo, that upon his ground nor tender conſcience ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to ſatisfie it ſelfe in a ſtayed condition, and if by a lye <hi>R. B.</hi> ſhall goe about to ſatisfie any (as he pretendeth that was the cauſe that moved him to anſwer my diſcourſe,) it will never doe it, ſuch are not much beholding to him, for neither they nor the truth needeth any mans lie, but I will forbeare to trouble thee further Courteous Reader.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the ſervice of Love,</hi> R. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155820:4"/>
            <head>A SHORT ANSWERE, TO A Paſſage in <hi>R. B.</hi> his Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N his Epiſtle he telleth the <hi>Reader,</hi> that there needeth nothing to be ſaid to overthrow the matter of the diſcourſe, then what is contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it, and this he ſaith is in a matter wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the whole building conſiſteth, but what now if <hi>R. B.</hi> miſſe in this, and be found to be deceived, as he was in his former Baptiſmes, then the whole building may, nay muſt be granted to ſtand. It is in the perp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tuity of the Church-Eſtate under the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and ſo of Baptiſme, by which I difference the matter thereof; The further ſaith, I make Baptiſme to depend on the Church; but what then? then he inſerreth that, unleſſe I be able to ſhew the continuedneſſe of the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> till theſe dayes, I cannot be aſſured that the Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me there is the Ordinance of God: But what if I can ſhew this, where is <hi>R. B.</hi> then? but he ſaith <hi>pag.</hi> 2, 3. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155820:5"/> I know none, nor doe I beleeve that any can ſhew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch continuance,</p>
            <p>But is worth the obſerving the evill dealing of the man, his willingneſſe to deceive, hee knoweth and the <hi>Reader</hi> may obſerve, I produced Scriptures to prove the perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Church in the World, ſuch as he nor any other are able to avoyde, or ſhew another ſence of them than that for which they were produced, I made an Inference from that in the 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> whereat he and others were much offended; Then I diſtinguiſhed thus, that this Eſtate of Chriſts-Church continued under <hi>Antichriſts</hi> exaltation, or elſe it continued ſomewhere elſe, as a part from under that deffection, for ſomewhere it muſt continue, that it continued any where elſe as in a pure way, I ſayd I did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve none could make it appeare, and therefore it muſt need continue under <hi>Antichriſts</hi> exaltation; and that it did not continue other where than under the deffection of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> I alleadged thoſe Scriptures of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalitie of the defection, and the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> being the firſt fruites to God, which could not be if the Church had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued any where pure, which it did not, but in defection it continued without being made <hi>null:</hi> what ever <hi>R. B.</hi> thinketh to the contrary, now what could be more plaine than this as in my diſcourſe may be ſeen: With what face then doth <hi>R. B.</hi> feed his <hi>Reader</hi> with ſuch a fable, and ſo abuſe his oppoſite, and triumph in his owne folly, and cry victorie; truly he in this dealeth with his oppoſite as the Divell dealt with our Lord, keeps back a mayne part, and ſo ſhewing a mind to ſmother the truth and keep it in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, I will appeale to any indifferent Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if it be not fully declared what is before ſaid, and that I hold the continuedneſſe of the Church-Eſtate, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the defection but not in a pure way, and if <hi>R. B.</hi> or any other thinke this a new opinion, it will but ſhew their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155820:5"/> Ignorance, for as learned and godly men are my Leaders herein, as thoſe hee catcheth at for advantage touching Baptiſme of Children, being a humane Ordinance, namely Mr. <hi>Junius Duplices</hi> Lord of <hi>Morney,</hi> the harmony of the Churches confeſſion and others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The holy Scriptures I ſhewed did hold forth the continuation, and perpetuity of the viſible Church, a plant of Gods owne planting, not to be rooted out for ever, as it had continued from</hi> Abraham <hi>to</hi> Moſes, <hi>from</hi> Moſes <hi>to Chriſt, ſo it ſhould continue for ever, for proofe whereof I ſet forth ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſcriptures, as in my diſcourſe may be ſeen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which <hi>R. B.</hi> in ſtead of granting or denying, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon a diſcourſe to prove a matter neither in queſtion, nor yet ever by any denyed, and in the end without ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any right ſenſe or meaneing of thoſe Scriptures, the better to informe his Reader, he flatly denieth the ſenſe of his oppoſite, and calleth him falſe Prophet, and on that hath ſpoken preſumptuouſly in the name of the Lord; a heavie charge: he onely inſtanceth in thoſe two Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that are propheticall, <hi>Eſay</hi> 9. 7. 59. 27. happily hee might feare there might be ſomething in the other, ſo he paſſed them by; But thus he proceedeth to reaſon, that if the viſible Church of Chrriſt hath not had a perpetuall, interrupted ſucceſſion in the World, ever ſince the firſt planting of it till theſe dayes; though the Propheſie bee true, yet the ſenſe of his oppoſite is falſe; here by the way I note how <hi>R. B.</hi> corrupteth his opponents concluſion with words of his owne coining, which words indeed are contradictorie, and plaine <hi>non-ſenſe</hi> in regard of the thing in hand, the matter in hand is the perpetuity or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuedneſſe of Chriſts Church in the world; he commeth with perpetuall interrupted ſucceſſion; this ſucceſſion he hath often in his anſwer, wherein hee juſt ſpeakes like a Parret; perpetuity and ſucceſſion cannot ſtand together,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155820:6"/> for where there is perpetuity of a thing there is no place for ſucceeding; ſucceeding or ſucceſſion may be in regard of an Office, one giveth place another ſucceedeth, and tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth place, but cannot be ſo with the Church, as in my diſcourſe may be ſeen: it may increaſe and decreaſe, but it alwayes abideth for ever, ſo as his ſucceſſion is an <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus</hi> if not a Bull: But he commeth to anſwer, hee will <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121. 1.</note> make my owne matter confute mee, I ſaid the defection was univerſall, I ſo ſay ſtill; as ſaid the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> in regard of purity were the firſt fruits unto God: he ſaith ſo too: But it is much he will acknowledge them ſo to be (hee may wrong his cauſe ere he is aware, they were not Diſciples by totall dipping, the French Churches proceeded of them <hi>R. B.</hi> might have been baptiſed by them, they were the firſt fruites as he confeſſeth, ſo as he and his toall dippers cannot be it or them: but where did I ſpeake of, and prove the univerſality of the defection, not to prove the utter ceſſation of the Church-State. <hi>R. B.</hi> cannot be ſo blind, but to manifeſt that it continued not in a pure way as a part from the defection, but under the defection I ſaid it muſt needs there continue: and the errour and abſurditie of ſuch an opinion I deſired any to ſhew if they could, ſo as had not <hi>R. B.</hi> been a vain Caviler, he would not have left the plaine matter and drift, as he hath done, and by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out the diſtinction with the drift, made a part, as if it were ſome other thing; But now further as he granteth the largeneſſe of the defection, and the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> to bee the firſt fruites to God, ſo he confidently denieth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuedneſſe of the Church-State in the World, eſpecially under the defection, but let his reaſons be weighed, firſt is becauſe it was given to him, namely <hi>the man of ſinne that ſitteth in the Temple of God) to make Warre with the Saints, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Rev</hi> 13. 7.</note> 
               <hi>to overcome them,</hi> a weighty reaſon thus: muſt needs die or ceaſe to be, becauſe overcome, a perſon is overcome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155820:6"/> when he yieldeth ſubmitteth himſelfe, ſo a Kingdome and a Citie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet they ceaſe not to be, Beſide it was about parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Saints that were overcome; what is this to the ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the whole Church? this reaſon is ſo lame, it had need of another to ſupport it, which he addeth to as little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if to overcome then they could not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue; wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: ſo before: yet further he ſaith, <hi>if the Church continued he did not overcome them and kill them with the ſword,</hi> Rev. 13. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Some of the Members might bee killed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.</note> as <hi>Antipas</hi> was, that faithfull Martyr: the Church-Eſtate or all the Churches of Chriſt killed with the ſword, and ſo overcome, is reaſon without ſence, ſuch as <hi>R. B.</hi> himſelf will not believe, when he hath better conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of it, if ſome of the Members of <hi>R. B.</hi> Church were killed with the ſword, yet he would thinke his Church might continue, yea if all of them were ſo killed, yet he cannot but think the Church might continue ſome where elſe, but belike feareing his reaſons to be weake he hath a further reaſon to prove the Church did not ſo continue, <hi>Thoſe that worſhipped the Beaſt were ſuch whoſe names were not written in the Lambes booke of life,</hi> therefore the Church <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.</note> it could not continue, what the ſtrength and force of this reaſon is, is beyond my capacity till it be explained: reprobate men <hi>worſhipped the Beaſt, ſo they worſhipped the Calves of old, and Idolls of Gold and Silver, and their Gods</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe.</hi> 13 2. <hi>Pſal</hi> 106. 36. 38. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er.</hi> 2. 28.</note> 
               <hi>were as their Cities,</hi> what is that to the ceaſing of the Church? <hi>R. B.</hi> had need goe to Schoole to learne ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger reaſons, it is no marvell he ſhould be ſo confident: he fulfilleth the Proverb, none ſo bold as b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind <hi>Bayard:</hi> but he goeth on further in this his perverſeneſſe, and ſpeaketh of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and would make his <hi>Reader</hi> beleeve I hold no Church-Eſtate remaining among them, becauſe I ſaid there is little difference in their defection, and the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt, and they will ſtand and fall together; being meaſur'd by a like meaſure.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:155820:7"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> they will ſo ſtand together as that the Church-Eſtate will remaine in the one and other, whatſoever <hi>R. B.</hi> is able to ſay to the contrary, after this hee taketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of what elſe where, he conſealeth of the Chuches continuance elſe where, might have added in a pure way: I ſaid I ſuppoſed none was able to make appeare, ſuch a continuedneſſe to have been in the World, if any could I ſaid and ſay ſtill, I ſhould be glad; and were it not a matter to be glad of it, would not <hi>R: B.</hi> be glad alſo; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily he would be ſorry, becauſe his new way would bee diſparaged, yea indeed overthrowne, and he foreced to be baptiſed a fourth time: But having thus gone on, he ſaith who can beleive his expoſition of <hi>Eſay</hi> 9. ſeeing he to witt his oppoſite, teſtifieth that none is able to make the truth thereof (of what of the Church in purity her continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? but in defection under the <hi>Greeks</hi> &amp; <hi>Romaniſt</hi> it may be made appear, where will <hi>R. B.</hi> be then among thoſe falſe Prophets he ſpeaketh of: but further? here he ſaith it muſt follow (right or wrong) that I have given a falſe Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of <hi>Eſay</hi> 9. and alſo of all the Scriptures, to prove the perpetuity of the Church, and none ſhall bee able to cleare me. But where is that true Interpretation of <hi>R. B:</hi> that might informe his <hi>Reader?</hi> he hath not ſtudied it yet, unleſſe it be that the Church is ceaſed, let the Scripture ſay what it will, becauſe otherwiſe his opinion cannot ſtand, ſo he proceedeth that thus having confuted my ſelf, he thinketh it needleſſe to ſpend time in the confutation of it; It was time ſpent indeed vainely for him to meddle; unleſſe he had better underſtood what he tooke in hand, after he falleth a complaining of wrong done, for being blamed for not beleeving the Churches continuance in the World, then it ſeemeth they doe not beleeve the continuance, but the ceſſation they doe, they had need of better ground to beleeve againſt ſo many cleare Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155820:7"/> then yet <hi>R. B.</hi> hath found out; but how ever I did not miſtake their judgement, in that I ſaid there was no ground for their practice, till they did beleeve ſuch a ceſſation, which they doe, and ſo their practice is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on a groſſe errour, and a flat denyall of the Scripture: cleare it if they can, but having ſo marvellouſly quited himſelfe, as he thinketh, he complayneth further, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſed for making Chriſt a Widower;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the viſible Church was Chriſts wife, and it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as you beleeve and, hold and remained without being: for a long ſeaſon was not Chriſt a widdower then and all that time? if he would but be pleaſed to minde the 5th. of the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> he would confeſſe it, Chriſt ſometime had a Church but he loſt it, is he then to day as hee was yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day? obſerve what tautologie hee here uſeth, or <hi>non-ſenſe,</hi> perpetuity and ſucceſſion, which I would not mention, for I thinke he is no great Artiſt as well as my ſelf, ſave only he ubraided me with it in his Epiſtle, he asketh me whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would have them to beleeve that I cannot beleeve my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I can beleeve and doe, the Churches continuance in the World, under the defection of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> if they did beleeve ſo too it would pleaſe me well, and ſure there would be no place for their unwarranted proceed:</p>
            <p>But this of being charged with making Chriſt a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dower ſticketh neere his ſtomack, hee cannot digeſt it, therefore he hath a lame conſequence about it ere he let it paſſe: If Chriſt be a Widdower, if he have not alwaies a viſible Church in the World, then hee inferreth that there is no ſalvation out of the viſible Church, Indeed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily the learned have held there is not, but extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily there may: but what then? thinking belike there was litle in this, he addeth none can be ſaved which are not firſt united and made one with Chriſt, whether he meane uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155820:8"/> of Faith or Order is hard to be ſaid, ſuppoſe union of Faith what is that to the queſtion in hand? and I would aske <hi>R. B.</hi> what ſhall become of Infants, but becauſe he propoundeth it as an inconvenience, attending the hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the perpetuity of the Church, and ſo asketh me the queſtion which he might have ſpared, till he could reſolve what ſhould become of Children dying in Inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncy, I ſhall anſwer, that <hi>John Hus,</hi> and <hi>Ierome</hi> of <hi>Frague,</hi> and other holy Confeſſors of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> they had union with <hi>Chriſt</hi> by Faith, which is firſt and maine, yea they had relation to the Church, though in deep defection, ſo as he publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his hope in vaine, he ſaith further if they were uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then <hi>Chriſt</hi> may have a ſpouſe, although no viſible Church in the World; but he doth but ſay it, wee may chuſe whether we will beleeve him. It is as much <hi>non ſenſe,</hi> as if we ſhould ſay <hi>Chriſt</hi> may have a Spouſe, though hee have none, ſure <hi>R. B.</hi> grew dull and much forgot himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The next <hi>Section</hi> containeth for the moſt part <hi>tautology,</hi> the man delighting to ſport himſelfe like a foole with his owne bable, onely he had a minde to aske me a queſtion which I ſhall anſwer in convenient place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. B.</hi> Proceedeth further, and hath another bout con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the perpetuity of the Church, carrying along with him his deviſed fable which he ſtill fathers on mee, without which he can ſay nothing, he tells his <hi>Reader</hi> that I ſay, ſeeing none can make it appeare elſewhere, he might have added in purity: he ſaith I ſay it is likely it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued under <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> ſo it ſeemeth he knew my drift, and did of purpoſe wreſt and pervert my words.</p>
            <p>But he here demandeth how it can bee probable, why, becauſe a little before I ſpake of the univerſality of the deection, I did ſo to ſhew no Churches remained a part in a pure way, therefore I ſaid there that which hee alſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155820:8"/> mentioneth here, that in that regard the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> were the firſt fruits to God they comming firſt out of defection into purity, but the 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. troubleth the man much, and that I alleadge it to prove the Churches continuance under the defection of <hi>Antichrist.</hi> This is a riddle to <hi>R. B.</hi> and he is as a in a maze, but hee anſwereth plainely here, that Temple here ſpoken of where the man of ſinne ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and is worſhipped cannot bee taken for the Church of God; but what is his reaſon, becauſe it is ſaid verſe the 3. <hi>the man of ſinne is not revealed, till firſt there be a departing:</hi> then <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10. he ſpeaketh of his deceiveableneſſe in the way of his comming, he asketh himſelfe a queſtion, and maketh himſelfe anſwer ſuch as it is, in whom ſaith hee not in the Church but in them that periſh; as if many of the Church might not periſh, ſure he forgetteth the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the ten Virgins, that five were wiſe and five foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</note> but doth <hi>R.</hi> B. indeed thinke that the myſtery of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity roſe, not in but out of the Church, that is a rare o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and ſingular judgement, which I never heard of before, and moſt contrary to the truth, for the Churches might have continued till now in purity but for the working of that myſterie, and beſide I would faine learne how it ſhould be a myſtery if ſimply in the World, not at all in the Church, I had like to have paſſed by his reaſon, the falling away is firſt, the revealing is after, what of this? when the man of ſinne which began to worke in the Church in the Apoſtles time had got ſome ſtrength, then he ſhewed himſelfe more fully; but he ſaith it muſt needs follow, that ſeeing the perſons the matter of the Church are departed from the Faith: therefore it muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low they are not in any wiſe to bee eſteemed the Church of God he doth but ſay this alſo we need not beleeve him <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106 28. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ch.</hi> 16</note> unles we will, but ſure this departing was not totall like their dipping, <hi>Iudah was departed from God and followed</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:155820:9"/> 
               <hi>Idoles,</hi> yet with <hi>Iudah</hi> was Gods Church, ſo it may be and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 16.</note> is under the defection for all his ſaying, in no wiſe it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, he would further inforce it from my judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and becauſe they that wonder after the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and follow him, are ſuch as <hi>are not written in the Lambs booke of life:</hi> It may be I am dull, ſure I underſtand not where the force of this reaſon lieth in regard of the matter in hand, what if I doe hold the Church may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of ſuch? many of whom may periſh, I thinke the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will maintaine me in it.</p>
            <p>But he hath a wonderfull concluſion, I doe not ſay it is preſumptuous, but ſure it is blaſphemous: his expoſition of 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. He ſaith the Temple there is no more the Temple of God than <hi>Antichriſt</hi> that ſitteth there is God, nor no otherwiſe to be eſteemed, nor hath any on more reaſon to affirme the one than the other, ſee if he doe not taxe the Spirit ir ſelfe, for the Spirit with more reaſon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth it, then <hi>R. B.</hi> hath reaſon ſo arrogantly to ſpeak as he doth. It were good for all ſober minded men to beware of ſuch deſperate contradictors of the word of God, weigh but the matter ſeriouſly; is there no more reaſon to affirme the one than the other, why doth the Spirit ſay he doth ſit in the Temple of God, what Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath God in the World but his Church? and that is called his Temple every where.</p>
            <p>The myſtery of inquity it roſe up in the Church, how <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> long it was before the Church was deſtroyed by it, <hi>R. B.</hi> cannot tell at the firſt, it was of the ſame nature being weake; as after when it was ſtrong, and was exalted to that height, all which weighed it will appeare, that <hi>R. B.</hi> had little reaſon to ſpeake preſumptuouſly as he hath done: he taketh what he hath ſaid for a full confutation, and that it cannot bee any ſuch continuedneſſe of the Church, and moſt impudently fathering a lie upon me he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155820:9"/> concludeth this matter: It muſt bee as <hi>R. B. pag.</hi> 2. ſaith, that under the defection of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> it could not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, but where are any ſuch words in <hi>page</hi> 2. or in any part of my diſcourſe, no marvell he that durſt be ſo bold with the Scripture, ſhould deale ſo by me, ſure his Church if it continue till they know it, will deale with him for it, for without &amp; not within is place for all liers, Thus I have <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 15.</note> followed him to and fro in this particular of the Churches perpetuity, and continuedneſſe in the World, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under the defection of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> I doubt not but it will appeare to be a truth for all <hi>R.</hi> B. hath ſaid, or is able further to ſay to the contrary, that he beleeveth it not I ſuppoſe it doth plainely appeare, that they in their way have no ground to goe on till this beleeved, namely the ceſſation of the Church, that their practice is grounded upon the denyall of a truth, fully held forth in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Churches perpetuity, let them ſhift it if they can, and in their next let them informe the <hi>Reader,</hi> the true ſenſe and right meaning of thoſe Scriptures by mee alleadged, and I only adviſe they take heed of falling into ſome familiſticall ſtraine, I have done.</p>
            <p>Now he proceedeth to Baptiſme and ſaith, ſuppoſe the Church hath continued, then Baptiſme by which the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is difference't co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth alſo, ſo it is probable his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is the Baptiſme of Chriſt derived from thence, <hi>R.</hi> B. hath forgot his queſtion, he asked me before, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſaid it was a bull: but what thinketh hee, is not the derivation good and rationall? he would have it taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, that the beſt ground his oppoſite hath is but proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. But it were well if he would once leave his fab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: I ſaid it was more than probable, and I thinke that is certaine if I miſtake not.</p>
            <p>But further he ſaith, ſeeing I hold Baptiſme dependeth on the Church: he addes true; and ſo maketh a hinge for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155820:10"/> his doore to goe up on, I would faine know where he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Scripture this true and falſe with reference to the Church, and Baptiſme, it will trouble him much to finde it: the Church is either the Church of God, or it is not, and ſo Baptiſme is either <hi>Chriſts</hi> Baptiſme or it is not, but of this by the way; in the next hee will happily ſhew it, then he proceedeth and taketh notice that I hold not the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of God, but that State I hold to be the mother of <hi>fornicaetion, Sodome</hi> and <hi>Egypt:</hi> he thinketh it muſt needs follow that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hath not the Baptiſme of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> he is ſo frequent in the change of Termes, as I might make a booke of it, I write of the <hi>Church</hi> and Baptiſme, the Ordinances of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing under that Roman State in that defection; hee is alwayes up with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Baptiſme thereof, hee cannot reach higher in his underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding but it muſt bee the ſame, and from that, that I hold the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> not the <hi>Church</hi> of God, hee will make it follow, whether it will or no, that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hath not the Baptiſme of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> will he make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appeare that Baptiſme doth not remaine the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of <hi>Chriſt</hi> under that State? who hath ſaid the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome?</hi> This he will make to appeare by a lame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thus, if the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hath not continued (what meaneth the man, it never was the <hi>Church</hi> of God, although God had a <hi>Church</hi> in the Citie of <hi>Rome)</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baptiſme by which the matter of the <hi>Church</hi> is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced, hath not continued in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſure this is a bull, the <hi>Church</hi> I indeed hold continued in the defection, and under the Roman State, though <hi>R. B.</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered a lie upon me and ſaid, I held it could not there continue, and as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Church,</hi> ſo Baptiſme by which the matter of the <hi>Church</hi> is differenced, not pure matter from corrupt, but matter from that which is none at all; as for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155820:10"/> true and falſe they are words of his own coyning as before, not found in the word of God.</p>
            <p>So as here hee taketh occaſion to anſwer a paſſage in in my diſcourſe, wherein I deſired any to ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he errour or abſurdity, hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t or damage t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commeth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, holdi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g the <hi>Church</hi> and ordinances to have continued under the defection, &amp;c. as in my diſcourſe may be ſeene. <hi>R B</hi> here ſaith, I may eaſily ſee it from wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I have written my ſelf: well, what is it? This it is that Baptiſme differenceth the true matter from the falſe, notorious fabler and falſiner! againe in his inference, if the Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſme of <hi>Rome:</hi> inſtead of in the defection: and thus he goeth over and over in his termes, be the Baptiſme of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which differenceth the true matter from the falſe, yet more of this coyne: It ſhould be, which differenceth the matter of the <hi>Church</hi> from that which is no matter, and the matter bejng ſo laid downe. Where then is <hi>R. B.</hi> his great abſurdity, that I may ſo eaſily ſee, ſure hee may more eaſily ſee his folly and baſe dealing, without true and falſe, and ſuch words of his owne foyſting in his inference, and pretended ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity vaniſheth in the ayre: but what <hi>Tautologie</hi> he here uſeth of this true and falſe, it is much to ſee men love the bratts of their owne braine. The ſumme of that great abſurdity that <hi>R. B.</hi> can ſhew of holding as before is ſet forth, is only, this Baptiſme under the defection diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renceth the matter thereof, the <hi>Church</hi> from that which is no matter at all, ſuch as are the <hi>Iewes, Mahometans,</hi> and other Heathen, and doth it not? and this is his great ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurditie: It were well for <hi>R. B.</hi> if no greater did follow of his holding the viſible <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be ceaſed out of the World, his cloſe this <hi>Section</hi> a is ſeeming contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction he ſuppoſeth in my tenent, wherein he ſtill abuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me and my <hi>Reader;</hi> he ſaith I affirme <hi>Rome</hi> is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Fornication, I doe ſo: and alſo that <hi>Rome</hi> is the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155820:11"/> true Spouſe of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> where have I ſaid ſo in all my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, he cannot end one <hi>Section</hi> without fathering ſome falſe matter on me.</p>
            <p>But with the leave of <hi>R. B.</hi> for more full ſatisfaction to the <hi>Read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> I ſhall ſhew that there is a different conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to be had of the <hi>Church</hi> in defection, and that it may be minded diverſly either in a good ſenſe, or in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, though he happily cannot ſee it, ſo as in on conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasion according to the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rupt defiled condition, it may be called <hi>Sodome,</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> the Mother of Fornication, and yet in ſome other ſence, and minding the Church of God, <hi>R. B.</hi> will ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d himſelfe both a Saint and alſo a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but this in a diverſe conſideration and reſpect, <hi>Iudah</hi> was the Church of God, and yet ſhe is called <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and an Harlot, and <hi>Laodicea</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 11. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi> 16. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v.</hi> 3.</note> yet in an other weighing; ſuch matter as was fit to be ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, the great abſurdity before lieth in <hi>R. B.</hi> his lame underſtanding. And now he commeth after his great tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell to conclude this matter thus, that ſeeing true Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me differenceth the true matter from the falſe, obſerve that without true and falſe he is aground and cannot ſtir, but he ſtill impudently will father this on <hi>P. B.</hi> and yet further ſaith I ſay ſo in my Epiſtle, where there is no ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to any ſuch purpoſe; he proceedeth in his concluſion, the Baptiſme of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not the Baptiſme o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> that differenceth the true matter from the falſe; a very worthy concluſion, a bratt of his owne braine plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him well, and ſo I leave him to hug his true and falſe; I ſhall now deſire the indifferent Reader to mind whether <hi>R. B.</hi> hath ſaid any thing to purpoſe againſt the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of the Church yea or no, or againſt the ſence of the Scriptures by me alleadged to prove the ſaid perpetnity.</p>
            <p>And alſo neither I did not ſay right, that there is no ground for their practice, till they hold this that the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155820:11"/> Church is ceaſed and not to be found in the World, which it ſeemeth to be very playne by <hi>R. B.</hi> that they doe hold, and ſo lay for the foundation of their practice, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, a foule errour; no marvell they bee no more ſtable, and ſetled, but ſtill in their changes, how forcible are right words? but what doth wrong reaſoning profit? it will never ſatisfie any tender conſcience certainly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. B.</hi> Proceedeth to Baptiſme, and taketh notice of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 6. 25.</note> what I ſaid, that if the Church be ceaſed then Baptiſme is ceaſed: here now he is ſomething more calme, he wants his true and falſe to help him out, to that he anſwereth, that although Baptiſme were ceaſed, ſo as there were no baptiſed perſon in the World: yet as long as Baptiſme is found in the word with a Commiſſion to doe it, he doth but beg the thing in queſtion never anſwering to what I objected in this caſe, here the 28th. <hi>Matth</hi> muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged but to what purpoſe, I ſuppoſe none can tell: Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme he ſaith may be obtained without any ſuch ſpeciall Commiſſion as had <hi>Iohn,</hi> if an unbaptiſed perſon ſhall doe it. <hi>R. B.</hi> will excuſe him of running before hee is ſent, though God never ſpeake one word to any ſuch ſo to doe: But he ſaith it will follow no more to be unlawfull ſo to doe: then it will follow that becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> might <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. 21. 7. 22.</note> not circumciſe himſelfe, and Males before circumciſion was inſtituted, and he commanded ſo to doe, therefore the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> ſee the weakeneſſe of the man in his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he ſhould ſay therefore the <hi>Philiſtimes</hi> or other Heathen might not circumciſe themſelves after. Indeed ſo he had overthrowne himſelfe: for they might not, though Circumciſion was inſtituted and commanded: yet they muſt goe to <hi>Iſrael</hi> as I urged the going to <hi>Sion,</hi> and there lighting their candle, as the Heathen of old did to <hi>Iſrael</hi> which he paſſeth by with ſilence, here is <hi>R. B.</hi> his Argument, Circumciſion is inſtituted and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155820:12"/> therefore the <hi>Philiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes, Aethiopians,</hi> and other Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then might circumciſe themſelves and their Males, I ſuppoſe hee holdeth not ſo; if he doth hee holdeth contrary to the truth, and this is the very caſe, which <hi>R. B.</hi> pleaſeth himſelfe withall; but hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth further, and argueth upon the point of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, It was neceſſary for <hi>John</hi> to have Commiſſion, as it was neceſſary to have a patterne for the firſt building of the Temple; but here hee evadeth from the Commiſſion to the Pattern, and ſo deceiveth the <hi>Reader:</hi> I would faine know of <hi>R. B.</hi> whether they had not a ſpeciall Commiſſion to build the ſecond time.</p>
            <p>It is ſure they were not onely ſtirred up, but bid goe up <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 7. 8.</note> and build the houſe, and God would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ercifull to them: But now <hi>R. B.</hi> tell me becauſe there was a Temple de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the word, and that was ruined and overthrown, might they build it againe before God bid them? might they build it in any place? and which is more and indeed to the life of the matter, might any but thoſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> build it? I am ſure it was ſaid to others it was not fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them ſo to doe, though the patterne was in the word, as in like manner it belongeth not to unbaptiſed perſons to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſra.</hi> 4. 3.</note> though the patterne be in the word, it is onely for ſuch as are baptiſed.</p>
            <p>To that objected that the Commiſſion 28th. <hi>Mat.</hi> It was onely to baptiſed perſons, and intendeth none other; <hi>R. B.</hi> anſwereth it requireth all perſons as are made Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, or ſhall be to be baptiſed, if hee had inferred that it is moſt likely there ſhall bee a continuance of baptiſed perſons in the World, that ſo his pleaſure might bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved he had ſaid ſomething: but he ſaith Chriſts voyce muſt be obeyed, therefore he concludeth a neceſſity, to doe as they doe: run before they are ſent, baptiſed they muſt be, why have they not a little patience? baptiſed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155820:12"/> perſons there are none in the World, yet another lie muſt be fathered on <hi>P. B.</hi> to make good the matter, hee believeth none in a pure way, but under the defection there might be ſome alwayes found, <hi>R. B.</hi> might know I reaſoned from their ground and practice, and not from my owne judgement, if he were not blind or a vaine Caviller as I told him before.</p>
            <p>But it appeareth to be true, that <hi>R. B.</hi> indeed holdeth ſo, that at ſome time lately there were no baptiſed perſons in the World: And yet Baptiſme might be raiſed againe well enough; there being none, how then? why ſaith hee in the. <hi>Time:</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. <hi>The Scripture is profitable and ſerveth for inſtruction in all righteouſneſſe to perfect the man of God unto all good workes,</hi> as is there declared, if to all ſaith hee then to this of Baptiſme: <hi>R. B.</hi> upbraided me for miſapply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture, but it were well if <hi>he had firſt ſeene the beame in his owne eye, and caſt it out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> truly this is a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing that ſo rare a practice ſhould have no better ground: the Scripture did not furniſh the Heathen to circumciſe themſelves to erect a Church among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to offer Sacrifice, yet theſe were good workes: It was a good worke to build the Temple, yet the Heathen were not furniſhed to doe it as before, God is the God of order which when it is neglected, for breach of due order he is offended, he is diſpleaſed as in the caſe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah:</hi> it was not for <hi>Saul</hi> to offer ſacrifice though it were a good <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 6. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 12.</note> worke as it is not for an unbaptiſed perſon to baptiſe: though <hi>R. B.</hi> doe fooliſhly inforce it by vaine confidence, the Iron was dull that he needed to put to his ſtrength: But let us ſee what it is he thus confidently affirmeth, that as at the firſt <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> at the command of God bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed others, though unbaptiſed himſelfe, even ſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his example written for our learning we are taught what to doe in like caſe of neceſſitie, he at length
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155820:13"/> is arrived at a faire haven, neceſſitie hath no law, being in a great ſtraite indeed, brought upon themſelves by their erroneous ground, of holding no baptiſed perſons in the world, after the example of diſobedient <hi>Saul,</hi> being in great ſtraite, they are bold to baptiſe others, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſed themſelves, our Lord did not ſo, though he were the King of the Church, as I told them before, which he tooke no notice of: but yet further he ſaith according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 4. A diſciple at the command of Jeſus Chriſt, where is that command in the 28. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> this ſerveth at every turne, as true and falſe did before: it is foure times alleadged in this ſhort ſection be like to fill up, that he might ſeeme to ſay ſome thing, but it may not be counted Tautologie: but doth the 28. of <hi>Matthew</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand unbaptiſed diſciples to baptiſe others, ſure <hi>R. B.</hi> is miſtaken and never able to make any ſuch thing appeare.</p>
            <p>If any ſay <hi>Johns</hi> example is extraordinary, and ſo not exemplarie: he anſwereth, theirs is an extraordinary caſe, truely ſo it is: without the rule of the Scriptures: but it may be <hi>Davids</hi> eating of the Shew-bread will ſtand them in ſtead. Indeed, in the caſe of extreame hunger to preſerve life it might: in exſtravagant courſes, ſuch as cannot be warranted by the Scriptures, ſome have done as here <hi>R. B.</hi> doth, catch at <hi>Davids</hi> example, upon ſome caſe of neceſſitie, to doe that which is not lawfull; this is their caſe he ſaith, and hereby he ſaith, they juſtifie their practiſe, but how well, let all men judge. But ſure <hi>R. B.</hi> forgot himſelfe in this, or otherwiſe he diſſenteth from others of his judgement. There were baptiſed perſons in <hi>Holland</hi> of a hundred yeeres diſcent and more, to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired thither were more eaſie, then for the <hi>Eunuch</hi> to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 8.</note> have gone to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> as eaſie it was, for them to have gone thither, as for our Lord to have gone over <hi>Jordan</hi> to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 13.</note> 
               <hi>John.</hi> If <hi>R. B.</hi> queſtion their baptiſme, it is much: happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155820:13"/> he may, becauſe they practiſe not totall dipping; then ſure it is likely, the reſtoration is but of two or three yeeres ſtanding, a very rare buſineſſe, and how rare are baptiſed perſons, he concludeth there needs no new com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to raiſe it againe, we may beleeve him if we will: All the reſt of what I wrote concerning this matter <hi>R. B.</hi> paſſeth over, not finding as is likely what to anſwer, in ſpeciall, that which I declared concerning corruption, not making a nullitie, he concludeth this matter with ſaying, their practiſe is not like that of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> and ſetting children againſt perſons of yeeres, he would make as if his opponent, were againſt the baptiſing of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, or perſons of yeeres, becauſe he holdeth the baptiſing of Infants: a fallacie and fond conceit, as if ſuch of old as ſhould hold the circumciſion of males at eight dayes, muſt needs be againſt the circumciſion of men of yeeres. But I muſt tell <hi>R. B.</hi> that it was unlawfull to rir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe thoſe of the ten tribes, when they were of yeeres, that had beene circumciſed, though in Apoſtacie in their infancie. And this is indeed the true caſe betweene <hi>R. B.</hi> and his opponent, if he could or would ſee it.</p>
            <p>New things are very pleaſing, and many are much taken with them, as is <hi>R. B.</hi> with dipping, about which he taketh great paines, produceth many Scriptures, and would ſeeme to be ſo ſtrong, as nothing is able to withſtand him: Firſt, he ſaith, I am greatly offended, he doth but ſurmiſe, for he cannot gather it out of my diſcourſe; he ſheweth what dipping he meaneth, total dipping of the whole man over head and eares; he pretendeth this is the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, wherein the 28. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> this now muſt ſerue the turne, as true and falſe did before: but ſure it is a rare thing to gather it thence, for if dipping were there injoyned, yet ſure totall dipping cannot be: It is not ſaid goe dip all nations totally, or over head and eares, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155820:14"/> this totall dipping is ſome voluntary religion, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 10. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 23. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 38.</note> having a ſhew of wiſdome; as mens owne wayes have; he quoteth many places, and ſundry examples, but ſure the man is as one that looketh through a greene-glaſſe, he ſeeth all of the ſame colour, all and every of theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and examples are for totall dipping, the whole man in matter and burying of him under water; and I appeale to the judgement of the indifferent Reader, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any the leaſt ſyllable to any ſuch purpoſe: no marvell he ſhould check me for not beleeving of it; and ſo confidently to father his fancie, and erroneous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, on the holy Scriptures, and which is more to hold all the Churches, and Chriſtians in the World to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſed, but thoſe two or three that have been thus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally dipped: he is in a high ſtraine if he can keep it, I hold not dipping ſo neceſſary, but that a perſon baptiſed by ſprinkling, muſt needs therefore be eſteemed unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, I indeed acknowledge I hold waſhing the maine, as before I declared in my diſcourſe, and waſhing by the way of dipping, or by the way of ſprinkling, to have in them the ſubſtance of the Ordinance being wayes of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing; he is pleaſed to take notice of the Reaſons, I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, which is firſt that ſpringling can be but a defect in the quantity of the Element; I ſaid it is a wonderfull thing a nullity ſhould follow thereof: and is it not? to this he ſaith that he wondereth any ſhould eſteeme that an Ordinance of Chriſt, which Chriſt never ordained; but this is only to beg the matter, unproved: but the 28. <hi>Ma.</hi> 19. ſerveth ſtill; Chriſt hee ſaith never ordained ſprinkling, but dipping; therefore ſprinkling in Baptiſme is none of Chriſts Ordinance, and ſo by conſequence a nullitie; Thus eaſily in his conceit, and fully in his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he hath made the Baptiſme of not a few perſons in the world; If I ſhould make the like againſt his totall dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155820:14"/> he would not receive it, though it be his owne, <hi>Chriſt</hi> never ordained totall dipping by an unbaptiſed perſon: <hi>Ergo</hi> it is none of <hi>Chriſts,</hi> but a nullity, and by conſequence <hi>R. B.</hi> is yet unbaptiſed.</p>
            <p>He taketh notice of a ſecond reaſon I ſet forth, and that is of placing the ſubſtance of an Ordinance in the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickneſſe of a word, to this he anſwereth, that he placeth the ſubſtance of every Ordinance in its conformity to the word; ſo as defect and corruption make a nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I ſuppoſe he holdeth; but he propoundeth a caſe for diſcovery, ſprinkling is no more to bee eſteemed Gods Ordinance, then to prick the finger was to bee eſteemed Circumciſion, and he that would not take that for Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion might as well bee accounted a Critick as hee that will not take ſprinkling for Baptiſme; ſure <hi>R. B.</hi> hath but little aime in his paralell, ſprinkling at the moſt is but a defect in the quantitie of the Element for all this, I will make a caſe and leave the Reader to judge of it, if any unskilfull Circumciſer ſhould have left ſome little part of the foreskin through overſight, ſhould it have been a nullity and no circumciſion? I ſuppoſe nay: ſo if any ſhall miſſe in waſhing by ſhortneſſe in the quantity of the Element, yet it may bee <hi>Chriſts</hi> Ordinance notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, for that ſuch a defect or corruption doth not make a nullity thereof, And if any dipper in <hi>R. B.</hi> his way ſhould through ſome neglect or other accident, not dip the Crowne of the head as well as all the reſt of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy under water, I ſuppoſe <hi>R. B.</hi> had but little reaſon, if he ſhould not account it true Baptiſme in his way, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he proceedeth: and here I note how faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I dealt with them, and how fouly hee hath dealt with me, I ſet downe their opinion ſo right, as that hee doth not goe about to mend it, he for the moſt part fathereth this, and the other falſity upon me, and by change of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155820:15"/> phraſes altereth often the whole matter for dipping in Baptiſing, and againſt ſpringling or waſhing they produce that <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>Collo.</hi> 2. 12. of Buriall with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which ſprinkling they judge cannot import or hold forth: To which I in my diſcourſe anſwered, that ſprinkling or powreing water on the face doth hold our Buriall and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection alſo, and indeed I judge it doth, and ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding men will account whatſoever <hi>R. B.</hi> thinketh to the contrary, to this purpoſe I alleadged that in the 10. <hi>Corinth.</hi> of being baptiſed in the cloud and Sea: and the Scripture telleth us they went over on drie ground, to this <hi>R. B.</hi> anſwereth not, for indeed he could not, they were dipped, they were buried as ſaith the word: But here hee inferreth that by this reaſon they ſhould not bee ſprinkled; Why? becauſe, they had not water on them: But <hi>R. B.</hi> may minde, how they had the Sea on either ſide, and the Cloud over them; and were in the Water: That the Spirit accounteth Baptiſme, as it doth Sprinkling, and waſhing, as well as dipping; ſo, as Water is neceſſary for baptiſing, but the uſe of it may be divers, ſome more neere, and ſome more remote from the written manner, and full ſcope of the ordinance, and yet have the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Ordinance in it. And if <hi>R. B.</hi> could make the ſea divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as <hi>Moſes</hi> did and ſhould carry one of his diſciples into it they might be ſo Baptized as they were, I ſhall beare his deriſion and proceed, The Baptiſme in the Cloud and Sea, urged, pleaſeth him not, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeketh by a queſtion to intrap. firſt he would know whether I hold it the Baptiſme of Chriſt inſtituted <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. I let R. <hi>B.</hi> know I hold it the Baptiſme of Chriſt, as the ſpiritual meat and drink were that are there alſo ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and that it held forth and had an eye to that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme after ordained by Chriſt <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. as the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bread and drink there did &amp;c. And held forth the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155820:15"/> foode in the Lords ſupper the ſubſtance of all which was and is Chriſt, ſo as it is a verie pertinent inſtance and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample what ever R B. thinketh, But he hath a farther demande wherein he abuſeth himſelfe, and me and the reader, with one of his accuſtomed Fables; fathering a thing which was never my iudgement nor practiſe about ſprinkling. I let R B. know I hold water neceſſary in Baptiſme, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he can divide the ſea let him ſo Baptize, I ſhall not finde fault with him, his inference is vain about voluntary Religion, and will not help his Baptiſme gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at all.</p>
            <p>To that by me objected that the forceing Baptiſme thus to hold forth buriall, we loſe that which it holdeth forth equally with buriall: Namely, the ſprinkling of the Conſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce in the blood of Chriſt. <hi>Eſay</hi> 52. 15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 24. And the Laver of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and waſhing in the blood of Chriſt that bleſſed fountain <hi>Acts</hi> 22. 16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 21. 1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Re.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>R. B.</hi> anſwereth, denying that ſprinkling in the blood of Chriſt is required to be held forth in Baptiſme, to which I ſay it is an eaſie thing to denie a matter never ſo plain. I ſhall refer the matter to the judgement of the Godly wiſe, whether the outward waſhing in Baptiſme doth not hold out every way of cleanſing of the ſoule in the blood of the Covenant. Baptiſme is the outward way of waſhing away ſin. It was ſaid to <hi>Saul Acts</hi> 22. 16. Be baptized and waſh away thy ſin &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now ſprinkling with which <hi>R. B.</hi> is ſo much offended, is a way of inward waſhing away of ſin as before, and if <hi>R. B.</hi> pleaſe to conſider the Scriptures again in ſpeciall that in the 36. <hi>Ezek.</hi> He may if he be not overſwayed by preiudice, happily change his minde ſo as to ſee that ſprinkling both outwardly and inwardly hath in it the nature of waſhing to cleanſe, And though hee like an unwiſe man hath againe cenſured my iudgement &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155820:16"/> about this matter; he hath condemned me being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, for I tell him once againe I hold waſhing more fully according to the nature of the ordinance, but ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling being a way of waſhing to cleanſe cannot be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reiected; he hath ſomething further here, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I doe not underſtand his aime and drift, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to father any thing on him but what he holdeth I paſſe it by, and the rather becauſe it is but the repeating of the ſcriptures before ſet forth, he being mightily ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with his ſence of them; pleaſing himſelfe with his owne conceipt that ſprinkling for waſhing or cleanſing is borrowed from the ſhadowes under the Law, and ſo no whit to the purpoſe, and ſo he would put by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he manner as no way ſignificant but onely the matter, blood: ſure the ſpirit knew how to teach if we knew how to learne: I will ſprinkle cleane water upon them and they ſhall be cleane: againe the blood of ſprinkling, and our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſprinkled, Is there nothing in theſe and the like but onely ſo as to be borrowed from the Law, and that is all I ſuppoſe <hi>R. B.</hi> is deceived at the leaſt.</p>
            <p>But now to that other particular of waſhing in the blood of Chriſt, which I ſaid was alſo loſt by thus infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing dipping; He anſwereth that I am much miſtaken: Why how appeareth it? in the iudgement of the ſpirit he ſaith dipping is waſhing; ſo I ſay in like manner is ſprinkling alſo as before <hi>Ezek</hi> 36. But if dipping be waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then waſhing may be dipping: in a ſpiritual ſence ſure it is; where is <hi>R. B.</hi> then: But though dipping be a way of waſhing, yet all dipping is not waſhing, nor ſo inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, a thing may be dipped in water for other ends: as for inſtance, a <hi>Smith</hi> dippeth his hot iron in water, and intendeth no waſhing, he ſaith to waſhing by the way of dipping much water is required: Indeed totall dipping muſt have ſome quantitie, but leſſe then <hi>Iordan,</hi> or <hi>Enon</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:155820:16"/> rivers may ſuffice to dip a perſon over head and eares: he ſaith here it doth follow, that as dipping the whole man, &amp;c. it doth lively repreſent our buriall &amp;c. ſo doing it in much water, muſt import a full reſemblance of our waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the blood of Chriſt, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13. 1. To which I ſay, ſure our Lord did not thinke ſo of the quantitie of either water, or waſhing, as <hi>R. B.</hi> doth. <hi>Peter</hi> was indeed ſome way of his minde, it appeareth; our Lord tooke a Baſen: and he told <hi>Peter</hi> that would needs be waſhed all over as they will be by dipping, that he that is waſhed, needs not but to be waſhed in one part &amp;c. <hi>R. B.</hi> here ſure forgot <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 13.</note> himſelfe, the manner in the caſe of ſprinkling though much inforced, he would have to import nothing, onely the matter; but in the caſe of dipping, he will have the maner as eſſentiall as the matter. And the quantitie of the element he will have as ſignificant as the matter, to wit, water it ſelfe: But though he be partiall, it being his owne cauſe it muſt be borne: ſo he concludeth this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſaying, they doe not loſe by dipping, the hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth their waſhing in the blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and againe, he muſt father a falſehood on me about ſprinkling, ere he leave it: <hi>R. B.</hi> proceedeth, and taketh further notice of what I write, and ſetting down a part only, that doth not hold forth my meaning: but the contrary hee anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thereunto as pleaſeth him; I ſaid all doe, or may know, that a thing dipped is not therefore waſhed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is waſhing alwayes intended in the dipping of a thing in water, there is a waſhing by dipping I ſaid: <hi>R. B.</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, that much leſſe is that which is ſprinkled, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore waſhed; I argued to inforce waſhing as the maine thing, and dipping but an accident in the way of waſhing, as is ſprinkling in like maner, for as there may be dipping without waſhing, ſo there may be ſprinkling alſo; but he mindeth further what I ſaid, that a thing dipped is not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155820:17"/> therefore waſhed and made cleane. I ſaid waſhing is not alwayes intended, as before in the dipping of a thing, this I ſaid to inforce waſhing, as moſt fully ſignificant, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of the ordinance. To this he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, that much leſſe is that which is ſprinkled, waſhed, and made cleane, I ſay, a thing may be ſprinkled as well as dipped, and not waſhed, or made cleane, yet there is a way of waſhing and cleanſing alſo by ſprinkling, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 25. he ſaith, he hath proved that is waſhing, ſo I have ſhewed that ſprinkling is alſo; he ſaith, he that is dipped is waſhed, ſo is he that is ſprinkled alſo; he ſaith by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence he is made cleane, ſo far as the ordinance doth require, I ſay ſo alſo of ſprinkling, according to that which is the life and ſubſtance of the ordinance, the cleanſing of the ſoule in the blood of Chriſt, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. Surely <hi>R. B.</hi> will acknowledge that waſhing is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall thing in baptiſme, and that there are divers wayes or manners of waſhing. And that at the moſt dipping is but a way of waſhing; I ſay no more, but that to me it is an admirable thing, that any ſhould lay ſuch waight on that way of waſhing, as that all other wayes ſhould be nullities in their account; eſpecially, that waſhing the maine and principall thing in the ordinance, ſhould not be baptiſme, or the ordinance of Chriſt, when that ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holdeth forth our waſhing in the blood of Chriſt, that bleſſed fountaine, and cleanſing thereby.</p>
            <p>I declared what I thought the ordinary way of their waſhing to be by dipping the thing in water and rubbing or the like in thoſe countries where baptiſme was firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted: I ſaid it is yet the way, or manner of waſhing in ſome caſes, as may be ſeene in the Diers waſhing their matterialls in the river <hi>Thames: R. B.</hi> applieth this to baptiſme, as if I ſpake of that: ſure he was dull of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: he ſaith they doe practice ſo, namely dipping,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155820:17"/> and when I can prove he ſaith they dipped oft; they will dip often too; like enough ſo I ſay, for they are for all new things, right, or wrong: But <hi>R. B.</hi> tell me, did they not dip often to cleanſe in the ordinary way of their waſhing? looke but on your owne example produced, to prove dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, waſhing; was he not to waſh ſeaven times? doe not thoſe I mentioned dip, or plunge their materialls oft in water? <hi>R. B.</hi> carrying the matter in his aſſumed ſence, as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth me why I am offended with them for dipping but once? I told him that totall dipping was the thing I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt, for dipping by way of waſhing, not totall but of a part, I told him it was a laudable way, eſpecially in hot countries; <hi>R. B.</hi> ſaith further, that if they dipped by way of waſhing, at the firſt, then is dipping the good old way, <hi>Iere.</hi> 6. 16. a very poore concluſion. I reaſon in like caſe thus, if they eat the Supper in an upper Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or at night, or leaning, the concluſion would be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to no purpoſe; hee asketh why I reproach their practice? I anſwer, becauſe they urge that which they can never prove by one ſyllable of the ſcriptures, namely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otall dipping; and alſo lay ſuch load upon one way of waſhing by dipping, when waſhing it ſelfe is rejected; but <hi>R. B.</hi> ſaith, he ſeeth I love to wrangle: I ſay, he ſure loveth to pervert councell by words: he would not make his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">
                  <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b</hi> 38. 2.</note> believe I ſpake of baptiſme, elſe when I ſpake of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon waſhing: That I love to wrangle, he ſaith, appeareth becauſe in ſtead of dipping often and rubbing to cleanſe, I now ſay a little water ſerveth to ſet forth our waſhing in the blood of Chriſt as well as a great deale, and the waſhing of one part as the face as the uſuall manner is, as well as the waſhing of the whole man: I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge I doe ſo hold and am willing to be judged by the godly wiſe whether it be not ſo: For I reaſon thus, if a great deale of water be neceſſary in Baptiſme, then a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155820:18"/> great deale of bread and wine in the Supper by like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which indeed would carnallize the ordinance, and again if a great deale be neceſſary and the quantitie have ſuch force in it, then the greater quantitie the greater force and more full holding forth the fulneſſe of the blood of Chriſt; And ſo not ſome little brooke like old Foord, but rather the great ſea, for this argument wolud carry men <hi>ad infinitum,</hi> But truely I thinke one dro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſts blood to be of that force and efficacie, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e be but ſprinkled with it, it will purge our conſcience from dead workes: I would pray <hi>R. B.</hi> and all other to obſerve the place by me alleadged: not to prove Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme or the manner of it as he would ſeeme to take it, but to illuſtrate the thing in difference, touching totall dipping and waſhing but of a part, and a little water and much, For ſure I thinke <hi>R. B.</hi> his anſwer will be counted weake and unſound in that he ſaith a little water ſerveth not to ſet forth our waſhing in the blood of Chriſt as doth a great deale; as for that place produced <hi>Zacha.</hi> 13. 1. The Lord aimeth at the pureneſſe of the blood of Chriſt and unexhauſtibleneſſe of it: rather then at the much<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, for then a ſea the greateſt of all waters, rather then a fountaine would have beene expreſt, the which I leave to the judgement of the reader: <hi>R. B.</hi> his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning a part not anſwerable to the whole, is as weake as the former, he ſaith the waſhing of a part doth not ſet forth the cleanſing of the whole; whom ſhall we beleeve, our Lord or him? our Lord told <hi>Peter</hi> in all <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> 13.</note> caſes of waſhing (I do not ſay it was Baptizing as he would make the reader beleeve) that he that is waſhed, needed not but to be waſhed in one part, and is cleane all: in the 36. <hi>Ezek.</hi> ſprinkling it cleanſeth from all ſinne and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſure that place 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1. <hi>R. B.</hi> miſapplyeth in this caſe, here he yet againe fathereth a falſe matter on
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:155820:18"/> me but I muſt beare it; he in the end after ſome further impertinent matter, ſaith he ſuppoſeth I know Chriſt would teach his diſciples humilitie by that act: But what then doth he teach nothing elſe? doth he not teach that he that is waſhed needs not but to be waſhed in one part according to his Maſters will? and further alſo that he that is ſo waſhed is cleane all? and if ſo in this waſhing then ſure in that myſterious waſhing much more; But in his conceit to waſh a part is contrary to his own Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Ma.</hi> 28. The man is ſicke of totall dipping, but it may be he may recover.</p>
            <p>He ſaith further, my great objection is that totall dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping cannot be performed with modeſtie and ſhamefaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; I ſay I judge it cannot, and I thinke ſuch as are god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſe will thinke ſo alſo, But he ſaith I urged againſt them in the hot countreyes their dipping often and rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing to cleanſe; Now he ſaith I cannot determine how it may be done once; If I had not met with ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe oppoſite I ſhould have ſpared my ſelfe and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der much paines: did I ſay they dipped and rubbed in Baptiſme? fie <hi>R. B.</hi> Did not <hi>Naaman</hi> dip or waſh ſeaven times? do not thoſe I inſtanced in dipping oft their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terialls, by which the way of waſhing is ſet forth; If <hi>R. B.</hi> have no more to ſay to ſave his courſe from Immodeſtie he is in a poore caſe: Going in his owne way he ſaith ſurely I will conclude they put on a linnen garment: I will rather conclude ſuch are wiſe and modeſt above what is written, that ſhall hold totall dipping nad yet uſe a Covering, I ſuppoſe <hi>R. B.</hi> will hold ſo too, If he do not, ſome of his opinion doe I am ſure? It will follow they baptize the garments into the death &amp;c. of Chriſt, They doe ſo I iudge according to their opinion, here yet ſtill he fathereth a lie on me about ſprinkling; But he ſaith not their garments but the perſons in the garments, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:155820:19"/> if totall dipping be Chriſts Command and Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo far as covered, ſo far undipped: whether thoſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments made for ſuch uſe and ſo uſed are not as holy as <hi>Popiſh</hi> Veſtments I leave the reader to judge. He ſayth it muſt follow that they that ſprinkle baptize garments al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, I ſay it is onely accidentall if they doe, they have no deviſed garment for the uſe, they have onely common Cloaths; ſome conſcientious men in <hi>R. B.</hi> were true to their principles that have beene baptized in ſuch veſtments, will ſee that the defect hath made void their Baptiſme and that they are not to reſt in it but to be Baptized againe.</p>
            <p>What ſhould be the cauſe <hi>R. B.</hi> hath laboured ſo much in this matter of dipping and taken notice of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, I leave every man free to judge, for my part I take it to be as I ſaid before, It is new and the man is mightily taken with it.</p>
            <p>For I am ſure the reſt of the diſcourſe is as much againſt him, and in ſpeciall that which followeth, to which he ſaith nothing at all; There is one thing in the end of this matter of dipping which he doth not declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe about, Namely whether he learned this new way of dipping of the Romaniſt and Ignorant <hi>Welch,</hi> and whether he count their Baptiſme the Baptiſme of Chriſt, In his next I ſuppoſe he will doe it.</p>
            <p>Now he hath done with the Negative part of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and ſo he commeth to the affirmative part, how he quitteth himſelfe there may be ſeene by that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth; before he cometh to it, he ſaith I have ſpoken my minde againſt the ordinance of Chriſt: Certainly he is greatly miſtaken, I have ſpoken for the ordinance of Chriſt which he hath peremptorily condemned, and yet doth, denying the Baptiſme of all the reformed Churches &amp; ſepared Churches, &amp; alſo of all other Chriſtians either Reformed,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:155820:19"/> or yet in defection, only thoſe two or three excepted that have within theſe two or three yeeres, or ſome ſuch ſhort time, bin totally dipped for Baptiſme, by perſons at the beginning unbaptized themſelves, An opinion ſo rare and ſingular, ſo high and preſumptuous as I ſuppoſe all perſons godly wiſe will abhorre the verie thinking of it:</p>
            <p>Had not <hi>R. B</hi> ſo travelled through this matter of dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping I ſhould not have challenged him for ſlipping, as now I ſhall in the reſt of the matter remaining; Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dipping was none of the three particulars he would reduce my diſcourſe unto, as he told his reader in the end of his Epiſtle, I muſt crave pardon if I declare my thoughts touching <hi>R. B.</hi> that he ſure thought himſelfe guiltie of what I ſo marvelled at, Namely that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould thinke that every Corruption meeting with Gods ordinance deſtroyeth it forthwith, as if Sathan were ſtronger then God; And that alſo his thoughts tell him he is one of them that would pull up the tares with <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ma.</hi> 13. 29. <hi>Eze.</hi> 43. 8.</note> the wheate, and deſtroy Gods poſts with mans, as in my diſcourſe I obſerved it to be the veine of not a few, of which things he taketh no notice; But maketh mention of my firſt poſitive ground, and uſeth his skill of reducing it to a very narow compaſſe, and ſo ſhifteth it off without either anſwering the ſcope, the reaſons or Scriptures, by me produced, ſo as I might take that ground unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and ſay no more. But in as much as I tender the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverie of light and ſome clearing to the truth I will a little travell here further; The firſt ground in my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was the Covenant of Almightie God to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeede after him in their generations <hi>Gene.</hi> 17. I ſhewed it was an everlaſting Covenant both in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and in the extent made to a thouſand Generations <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. Continuing to the time of Grace, being of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:155820:20"/> force after the ſuffering of our Lord, that it did extend to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> they being a part of the ſeed to whom this <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 6</note> Covenant was made as in the diſcourſe may be further ſeene, none of all which <hi>R. B.</hi> denieth, for indeed he could not, but ſomething I further propounded, he catcheth and that is about the difference, I conceived to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a Covenant and Teſtament. That there's two Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments of Almighty God and one Covenant, diſtinct in divers conſiderations, and in ſpeciall in the manner of Confirming, which things <hi>R. B.</hi> refuteth not, though I deſired that any one ſhould ſhew the error that attends it; he after ſome confuſed and darke ſetting forth of the ground, Anſwereth he marvelleth I ſhould urge Infants being in a Covenant not confirmed by the blood of Chriſt, to prove their Intereſt in Baptiſme, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in the blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This matter he ſuppoſeth to be againſt me, To which I anſwer, the Covenant of Almighty God to <hi>Abraham</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 17.</note> and his ſeede was confirmed in Chriſt, and by him, rather in his birth and comming into the world, then by his death and leaving the world. <hi>Gala.</hi> 3. 17. But not to wade in new things I further ſay that that Covenant <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. was made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed the Church, The Teſtament by <hi>Moſes</hi> was made with the ſame people, old and young. The new Teſtament confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in particular wiſe with the blood of Chriſt it was made with the ſame people alſo, the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iuda:</hi> ſo as the matter ſtanding ſo, that the Covenants and Teſtaments whether ſo diſtinct or not (as before) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to yong aſwel as old, what cauſe had <hi>R. B.</hi> to marvell unleſſe at his owne ſhallowneſſe? for indeede to any that hath but halfe an eye it is ſo far from excluding Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as it doth wholly include them, and intereſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right them in the Covenant and Teſtaments both old
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:155820:20"/> and new, and ſo in the ſeale now as of old, eſpecially the Covenant being everlaſting and by neither Teſtaments made voide. But further he ſaith, If Infants be not in the Covenant confirmed by the blood of Chriſt who ſaith they are not: Then can they he ſaith have no right to Baptiſme. which ſerveth to ſet forth our blood of waſhing in the blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> But I anſwer if they have intereſt both in that Covenant and Teſtament alſo, then they may have right to <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> But this is moſt certain as before is briefly <hi>declared,</hi> ſo as if <hi>R. B.</hi> can ſhew no other eror to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that diſtinction, it will alſo as the reſt of the matter, paſſe for good, for any thing R. B. to purpoſe can ſay againſt it: But he ſaith this excludeth Children not only from Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, but alſo from ſalvation by Chriſt; how it doth ſo I ſuppoſe he cannot tell. If he thinke thus becauſe they are ſaid to be in a Covenant, not confirmed particularly by the blood of Chriſt, Though Typically and Relatively it be ſo confirmed.</p>
            <p>Then from ſuch a conceit it will follow certainly, that thoſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of old Parents and Children, were exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from ſalvation by Chriſt, they being in a Covenant not ſo confirmed: Indeed his opinion ſeemeth to be ſicke of this diſeaſe, for how Children which he holdeth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther within the Church, nor within the Covenant, nor doe beleeve, how they ſhould have ſalvation by Chriſt, ſure he cannot tell: This <hi>R. B.</hi> according to his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thinketh a ſufficient anſwer, The ſcriptures which I produced to prove the extent of the Covenant of God to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed in their generations; and that the Gentiles they were a part of the ſeed to whom the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was made, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3. 6. That children are included, and not excluded, ſo being in the Covenant and of the Church, have a writ now alſo to the Seale to be buried with Chriſt by Baptiſme, all which I ſuppoſe R. B. gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:155820:21"/> as true, and that he could not gain-ſay the ſame: And is therefore by juſt conſequence guilty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> offering wrong and violence to the Covenant of Almighty God, and to <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the faithfull; in excluding ſuch as God hath not onely included, but expreſſed in that his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.</note> Covenant and alſo in both his Teſtaments, for theſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo diſtinguiſhed, or otherwiſe: were made with one and the ſame people, the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iuda,</hi> ſo as to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</note> exclude Children alway included muſt needes be a chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Everlaſting Covenant and a bringing in a new Goſpel never learned of Jeſus Chriſt, and let R. B. or any other cleare themſelves of it if they can.</p>
            <p>The ſecond poſitive ground I ſet forth it was the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe and perpetuitie of the Church, ſome change be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in forme and Adminiſtration, but not in matter and relation, as in my diſcourſe is before fully proved; <hi>R. B.</hi> thinketh he hath diſproved the ſame and ſo here paſſeth it by: And he onely mindeth what I did infer from this ground. Infants I ſaid were lawfull members of the Church from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> from <hi>Moſes</hi> to Chriſt, what ſhould let them from being a part of the Church and lawfull members yet ſtill? ſeeing the Church or Kingdome is the ſame. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 43. I alſo there proved that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> they are fellow-heirs and of the ſame body. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3. 6. To all which and that that further followeth in my diſcourſe. <hi>R. B.</hi> anſwereth that though Infants were of the Church of old, yet the Lord hath manifeſtly declared they ſhall not be ſo now; It would amaze one to ſee the preſumptuouſneſſe of the man; hath God ſo manifeſtly declared their putting out of his Covenant and cutting off from the Church, where is that manifeſt declaration? the ſcripture rather decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth their continuance <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3. 6. But let us ſee where is that manifeſt declaration, It is <hi>Gala.</hi> 4. There is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:155820:21"/> in the ſcripture but of one Allegorie and that is all the proofe <hi>R. R.</hi> hath for the excluding of Children from the Church and cutting off their entayle from the Covenant, ſure he is verie neare driven that hath no other proofe but this Allegorie to prove a matter of ſuch great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as the altering of the unchangable Covenant of God and cutting of a part of the Church, And this Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie muſt be expounded, according to his owne ſence and fancie or elſe all is loſt with him in the cauſe, But let us ſee how he maketh the Allegorie ſpeak to his purpoſe, for the putting of Infants out of the Church: <hi>Gala.</hi> 4. It is written <hi>Abraham</hi> had two ſonnes one by a bond-maid an other by a free woman; he that was borne of the bond-woman (to wit <hi>Iſhmael)</hi> was borne after the fleſh, but he that was born of the free woman was born by promiſe, The ſum of all this is that <hi>Iſhmael</hi> not being the childe of promiſe, was put out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> family: Alas what is all this to the manifeſt declaration? O yes ſaith he it is an Allegory but ſure <hi>R. B.</hi> had ſmall judgement and leſſe reaſon to ſay an Allegorie is a manifeſt declaration: But happily he may make ſomething of it; I ſhall minde his ſence, The bond-woman he ſaith ſhadowed out the old Covenant: and her ſon <hi>Iſhmael</hi> which ſhe bare to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> after the fleſh by carnall generation: ſee what words <hi>R. B.</hi> here uſeth in ſetting out the generation of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ſure there was ſome Allegorie in his thoughts about them; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 19.</note> For I askt him, was not <hi>Iſaac</hi> borne after a fleſhly wiſe, and by carnall generation alſo? ſure he was begotten and brought forth even as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was, <hi>R. B.</hi> is yet beſide the white; hee further ſaith that <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ſhadowed out the carnall <hi>Iſraelites</hi> which ſhould proceede from <hi>Abraham</hi> in after generations, to what time he referreth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 9. 6, <hi>Act</hi> 3. 25.</note> this, it doth not appeare: As under <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> are ſaid to be a holy people, and Gods peculiar treaſure, ſo
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:155820:22"/> after Chriſt the Apoſtle telleth us expreſſely they were the Children of the promiſe, If <hi>Iſhmael</hi> being caſt out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe Gods Church for mocking; did Type out the unbeleeving <hi>Jewes</hi> that rejected the Son of God, as indeed it did, if R. <hi>B.</hi> held ſo, I agree with him but ſure he meaneth ſome other matter, and therefore he goeth on further and ſayth, The free woman <hi>Sarah</hi> pointing out the new Covenant and <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> But can <hi>R. B.</hi> put no difference betweene the new Covenant, and the Church in his judgement: that is from above and her Sonne Chriſt: Some of the Covenant or Church meaneth he; ſure Chriſt came of the Church of the <hi>Jewes</hi> as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 5. <hi>R. B.</hi> will not account that <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> from above, he will confound himſelfe, and loſe all if he take not heed before he get out of the Allegorie, or bring his manifeſt declaration to light; he addeth Chriſt the promiſed ſeed. <hi>Gala.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>R. B.</hi> doth not take Chriſt here perſonally, for then it muſt be excluſively, (I ſuppoſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 13.</note> to all others) but he taketh it, I judge, myſtically and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively for him and all his, the Children which God hath given him whether <hi>Jewes</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> males or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males young or old.</p>
            <p>For his ſaying in this place not to ſeeds as of many, but to ſeed, as of one that is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Is as I conceive not of <hi>Iewes</hi> apart as on ſeed &amp; <hi>Gentiles</hi> apart as another &amp; ſo ſeeds, but both together in one to wit in Chriſt as it is written <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 16. &amp; I paralell this place with that in the 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12. where the Apoſtle ſpeaketh after a like manner &amp; I leave the reader to judge of it; But to go on he ſaith as Chriſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſe.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the ſeed, ſo believers born from above or by promiſe; ſure he meaneth actuall beleevers, ſo as to be capable of totall dipping, certainely <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not ſo borne from above, when he came firſt into the world, and yet then he was the ſonne of promiſe, and <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeed. <hi>v.</hi> 29.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:155820:22"/> 28. He further urgeth that we as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was, are children of the promiſe, we <hi>Gentiles,</hi> we <hi>Galathians</hi> are as <hi>Iſaac</hi> children of the promiſe: how was he by deſcending from <hi>Abraham</hi> of <hi>Sara</hi> Lineally? can any thing be brought more plaine for the manifeſt right of Children to be of the Church and within the Covenant, then that which <hi>R. B.</hi> would bring to exclude them? <hi>Iſaac</hi> the ſonne of of <hi>Abraham</hi> by <hi>Sara,</hi> before he came into the world, when he was an Infant of aday old was the childe of promiſe, aed ſo were all the ſeed of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Church of old, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Apoſtle <hi>Peter Acts</hi> 3. 25. In like manner we <hi>Gentiles</hi> are as <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſo children of the promiſe and have <hi>Abraham</hi> for our father and the father of all our ſeed, the bleſſings of <hi>Abraham</hi> being common, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> through <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 36.</note> faith (as the <hi>Iewes</hi> loſt it through unbeleife,) God to be the God of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> by ſpeciall relation and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and the God of all their ſeed, as of old he was to <hi>Iſaac</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> &amp; to all the generation that followed.</p>
            <p>But <hi>R. B.</hi> ſuppoſing the matter not to be yet cleare enough travelleth further in the buſineſſe and ſaith, that to cloſe up the full intent of the ſpirit the Apoſtle <hi>ver.</hi> 29. 30. ſaith that the carnall and fleſhly ſeed <hi>Iſhmaell</hi> for perſecuting was with his mother caſt out; out of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> houſe the Church: Well now <hi>R. B.</hi> draweth nigh to his manifeſt declaration, which is that by their caſting out was foreſhewen, that when Chriſt the true <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhould be born (here he ſeemeth to underſtand that place <hi>Gala.</hi> 3. 16. perſonally &amp; ſo excluſively.) And the barren <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 54 1</note> woman, the new Covenant or Goſpell, A rare under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: The barren woman I had thought had been the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and ſure ſo it is, and not the Goſpell or new Covenant; for did not the Goſpel alwayes in the ſence <hi>R. B.</hi> is now in opening his Allegorie alwayes, bare Children to God? ſure it did witneſſe the Catalogue of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:155820:23"/> the faithfull <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. Further he ſaith then ſhall the bond-woman, which he calleth the old and carnall Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, with all the Carnall ordinances thereof: This is a very rare ſence alſo the covenant of Almighty God by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> he calleth Carnall; certainly it is a Carnall expreſſion and unſavorie ſo to call that gracious Covenant of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God which hee of love and free Grace gave or made unto his people <hi>Deu.</hi> 33. 6. and to call thoſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ordinances of Gods own Inſtituting, how ever ſome way Ceremoniall, to call them Carnall after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Carnall or Common Generation: But further he ſaith that all her ſonnes the Carnall and fleſhly ſeed <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> and all becauſe begotten and borne of the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh, ſhall bee caſt out of the houſe: It doth not ſay caſt out Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Church for the matter ſo far travelled in, is where it was if not worſe and further off.</p>
            <p>Caſt out <hi>Agar</hi> and <hi>Iſhmaell, Abraham,</hi> out of thy houſe, for they ſhall not inherit with <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Sara</hi> as indeed they did not, And therefore as the ſum of all <hi>R. B.</hi> ſaith that though Children of old were of the Church and within the Covenant before Chriſt yet they are not now if we pleaſe to beleeve him, Children it ſeemes are great loſers by Chriſt coming: But Alas is this the manifeſt declaration, that <hi>R. B.</hi> fathered ſo confidently on Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, in rejecting Children from being of the Church. Truely I ſuppoſe he and ſuch of his way, had more need to be pitied for their ignorance joyned with preſumption, then to be envied for any rareneſſe in their opinions; he further ſaith my expoſition of this ſcripture <hi>page</hi> 22. in my diſcourſe, is alſo to be rejected and caſt out, and his rare expoſition is to bee received and taken in: For hee ſaith in my diſcourſe I make ſuch onely to be the ſons of the Bond-woman as actually refuſed and rejected Grace as <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. 35. 36. He meaneth <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 11. and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:155820:23"/> bound, I ſaid there as the reader may ſee that theſe two ſons which <hi>Abraham</hi> had by two women, were two Types, And the Apoſtle ſaith it is an Allegory and they did Type out two ſtates of people, and had reference <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3.</note> to the time of Grace when Chriſt came unto his own and they received him not <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 11. but to ſuch as, did hee gave power to be the ſons of God; But ſuch as did not as the greateſt number of the <hi>Iewes</hi> did not they became bond and were caſt out; the kingdome being taken from them and given to others, namely the <hi>Gentiles</hi> &amp;c. as fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 36. <hi>Gala.</hi> 4. 28.</note> may be ſeene, which rejecting and caſting out the holy Apoſtle ſo greatly bewayleth <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 11. The <hi>Iewes</hi> for unbeliefe were caſt out as was <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Agar</hi> for mocking, But ſuch of the <hi>Iewes</hi> and Gentiles alſo that did beleeve were made free by the ſonne that maketh men free indeed: I ſaid thus this Allegorie is fulfilled and we <hi>Gentiles</hi> are as <hi>Iſaac</hi> and as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> children of the promiſe. This underſtanding muſt he ſaith be caſt out al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and he ſuppoſeth he hath a ſpeciall reaſon for it; for <note place="margin">Ioh. 8</note> ſayth he this implyeth as if they had beene free by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Sure the man dreamed, they were free as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was by promiſe, being a part of the ſeed to whom the promiſe was made, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> they were ſo free by promiſe as they could tell our Lord: but they were not ſo free, but that they muſt become bond, unleſſe they were further <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.</note> made free by the Sonne that maketh men free indeed: Rejecting of him they of free became bond, and are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day and cut off, but ſhall be looſed againe when their hearts ſhall be turned to the Lord, and they grafted into their Olive tree againe: But this <hi>R. B.</hi> ſaith is a manifeſt contradiction of the Apoſtle, let that bee made appeare; thus hee doth it; The Apoſtle hee ſayth by the bond-woman underſtandeth all them that were borne as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> by fleſhly generation, hee then as I
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:155820:24"/> ſaid muſt meane <hi>Iſaac</hi> alſo, for he as before is ſhewed was ſo borne by fleſhly generation, though <hi>Abraham</hi> was old and <hi>Sara</hi> ſtricken in yeeres, the intent and meaning of the Apoſtle is far otherwiſe as before is ſhewed, though he ſee it not: and ſo rudely to father his erroneous conceit upon the holy Apoſtle: So hee concludeth that all that are not as <hi>Iſaac</hi> by promiſe &amp;c. the <hi>Galathians</hi> bein <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> were as <hi>Iſaac</hi> by promiſe as before, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> being grafted into the ſtock of <hi>Abraham</hi> the Church their ſeed, though lineally deſcended is owned of God as of old, and after the manner of <hi>Iſaac</hi> Children of the promiſe.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe the indifferent reader will bee able to ſee how far <hi>R. B.</hi> is from making good, what he ſo boldely affirmed, And that the Children of the faithfull and ſuch as are of the Church, are yet ſtill true and lawfull Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and ſuch as are not to bee denied to come unto Chriſt of ſuch being his Kingdome; The reſt of what I ſet forth in my diſcourſe touching this ſecond poſitive ground in as much as <hi>R. B.</hi> happily was in his deepe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing, to ſome of the three heads before mentioned, I ſhall hold him excuſed for paſſing it by: If any reader ſtudious of this controverſie deſire to ſee further thereof, he may pleaſe to peruſe the diſcourſe. And ſo I proceed as doth <hi>R. B.</hi> ſaying my next ground is the Apoſtles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting Parents to bring up their Children, in the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Lord, therefore by conſequence they were of the Church and ſo baptized, I ſaid indeed the Apoſtle writing to the whole Church diſtributeth the ſame into parts, and maketh one part Children which he willeth to be obedient, and theſe were young and to be brought up in the feare of God: Now the Apoſtle writing to the Church would not meddle with them if without, I allude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that place 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. whether the alluſion were ſo proper yea or no I leave the reader to judge, But about
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:155820:24"/> this <hi>R. B.</hi> taketh paines and travelleth about it, and infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth this and that as abſurdities, to little purpoſe, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, in the meane time never clearing that which followeth of the <hi>Jewes</hi> Children, being left out when they ſhall be called and grafted into their ſtocke againe, as no more capable to be of the Church, which were greatly to leſſen their comforts and to diminiſh of the grace of God to them, But minding his promiſe of reduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he paſſeth over and commeth in his further proceed, to take notice that I ſaid it was an uncomfortable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, the excluding the Lineall ſeed of the faithfull from the Church eſtate and Covenant as of old, for from thence I ſaid it will follow that Parents doe beget, beare and bring forth children to the devill &amp;c. To this he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth that by nature we are all the children of wrath, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. To which I ſay, that indeed the <hi>Ephe.</hi> were the the Children of wrath before their calling and ingraft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Church; And further it is true of the ſeed of the faithfull, and of the faithfull themſelves, that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſidered according to their fallen condition and unregenerate part, they may be ſo minded, yea <hi>Iſaac</hi> the particular ſon of promiſe was ſo alſo: But by Covenant and promiſe, neither <hi>Iſaac</hi> nor yet the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were the Children of wrath, as were the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and their ſeede, But were the people and children of God, <hi>Eze.</hi> 16. Hee ſayth further that our being of the Church, dependeth on our regeneration; which I ſay is a Familiſtcall ſtrain: But he further ſayth, if all that are not borne members of the Church ſhall be damned. I ask who ſayth ſo? Doth <hi>R. B.</hi> know no difference betwixt theſe two, that in his judgement, the one muſt needs follow the other, being out of the Church, and ſo Relatively without God in the world; then they muſt be damned and there is no other way, If it were ſo, children would be in a poor caſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:155820:25"/> to his judgement that excludeth them all the church: But his drift is to inforce ſome abſurditie on me. I ſhall take notice of it: he ſaith there is in my judgement no true viſible Church in the world. This fable we had enough of before: ſo he Argueth on thus, no church, no Children borne in the Church: no Salvation: He asketh mee if this doctrine of mine be not verie comfortable: he may take it to himſelfe for ſure he is the Maſter of it: And by this fayned retortion, he thinketh to heale and comfort the ſad thoughts of Parents, againſt that dolefull conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that their children are not now as of old, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God; but are borne the children of the Devill: and ſo hee skippeth over what I inferred by way of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which it ſeemeth he had no liſt to anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. B.</hi> taketh notice of another Argument, which hee ſayth muſt needes be anſwered: for hee taketh it, I place great confidence in it, and indeed ſo I doe, he ſetteth it downe thus, Children of Beleevers are holy, therefore they may be baptized. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14. To this ſcripture ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and applied, as in my diſcourſe may bee ſeene, <hi>R. B.</hi> anſwereth, that the Apoſtle doth not ſay the children of beleevers are holy: ſure he hath little modeſtie, he might as well deny the light at Noone day; doth not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay now are they holy, v. 14. But what then doth the Apoſtle ſay, that the unbeleeving wife is ſanctified to the beleeving husband? that is to his uſe, ſo as his ox or ſheep and other goods are, I ſuppoſe he ſo meaneth.</p>
            <p>Could the <hi>Corinthians</hi> queſtion that a poor Expoſition, It is likely rather they queſtioned their lawfull continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with them: becauſe of old the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were to put away their ſtrange wives, and the children which were <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſra</hi> 10.</note> begotten of them: which children God did not own for his, ſo they might have conſcience of doing ſo alſo; The partition wall being now broken downe, the caſe it was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:155820:25"/> otherwiſe, and this <hi>R. B.</hi> in part confeſſeth as their ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but he ſeeketh to turne another way by multip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g words, and in the end maketh this the ſum of all, that their children ſo begotten (are Legitimate) that is, true borne not baſtards, a wonderfull caſe and rare expoſition! if one be a beleever then the children are true borne, but if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be, then the children are baſtards; what a number of Baſtards are there in the world, in <hi>R. B.</hi> his ſence? hee addeth as a reaſon of his expoſition, that the holineſſe of the childe is not concluded from the beleeving of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but from their lawfull uſe each of other: which is utterly untrue and contrary to the ſence of the ſcripture, that tearmeth the ſeed of thoſe of the Church holy for their relation ſake, but the ſeed of other not having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, uncleane, though borne in never ſo true wedlock. But <hi>R. B.</hi> againe ſaying the ſame without any ſhew of proofe, that it proveth no more holineſſe in the ſeed of the faithfull, then in the ſeed of the heathen borne in wedlock: But he doth but ſay it, we are not bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve him unleſſe we will; He intendeth brevitie he ſaith, and ſo referreth me further for anſwer of <hi>R. B.</hi> where the the matter is handled at large.</p>
            <p>Theſe he ſaith are the reaſons I can ſhew for baptizing of children, which becauſe they ſatisfie not ſome, but they require as well he ſaith they may, a precept or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for warrant. He ſaith I promiſe to doe that, but firſt requires a precept or example to be ſhewed of an unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized perſons; baptizing either himſelfe or others, and alſo the like for rejecting children their member-ſhip in the Church, and right in the Covenant as of old. Theſe two he hath ſufficiently done: Indeede if hee might bee his owne judge he hath, but truely he muſt to work about it againe, or otherwiſe, men of judgement will count his cauſe loſt, for <hi>R. B.</hi> to proove that an unbaptized perſon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:155820:26"/> may baptize himſelfe, or others, before he be baptized himſelfe; brings <hi>Davids</hi> eating of the ſhew-bread, and the Alſufficiencie of the ſcripture to inſtruct the man of God in every good work, And for cutting of the Intayle of children from the Covenant, and putting them out of the Church: that one onely Allegorie mentioned in the ſcripture, <hi>Gala.</hi> 4. and this expounded aright, and not according to his erroneous ſence, is ſo far from being for him; as it is cleare againſt him. It is no marvell he ſhould ſay it is ſufficiently done; It is well he is judge in his own cauſe, for ſure others, no not thoſe of his owne way will ſay any ſuch thing for him.</p>
            <p>Now he will take notice of the performance of my promiſe and ſo to the firſt thing by me ſet downe, he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cavelled at it before he paſſeth it by, Namely, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren their being baptized into <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Cloud and Sea: a verie cleare example.</p>
            <p>He mindeth my next as the firſt, and that is of the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing whole houſholds, as the Jaylers <hi>Lydiah,</hi> and the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold of <hi>Stephanus</hi> by <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe. <hi>R. B.</hi> replieth to this and ſaith, he requireth an example of Baptizing Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and not of houſholds. It is worth the noting, what unequall dealing may be found in men, and how far men are from meaſuring to others, what they require of others to be meaſured to them, to prove that an unbaptized perſon may baptize. <hi>Davids</hi> eating the ſhew-bread is a verie cleare example and full proofe with <hi>R. B.</hi> And he may take himſelfe wronged if any ſhall refuſe it. If I had ſaid to him I require an example, not of eating ſhew-bread, but of an unbaptized perſon, baptizing of himſelf, what would he have ſaid, he it is likely would have mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me of the ſubſtance of the thing, and the nature and agreement of the matter ſo parralled as he intended: I minde him ſo to minde this Inſtance and proceede.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:155820:26"/>
            <p> I reaſoned thus from theſe examples, If Children with their Parents entred not the Covenant Church, eſtate now, as of old they did: The Apoſtles would have ſpoken more particularly and not ſo generally, for ſure hee minded the reproofe of our Lord to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>marke</hi> 10. 14.</note> thoſe Diſciples, that hindred children from comming to him, for this reaſon amongſt other, becauſe the Church conſiſts of ſuch: It is an example for baptizing whole houſholds however, wherin uſually are yong children, It is as pertinent however, as <hi>Davids</hi> eating the ſhew-bread before: A family may be tendred, a whole family may be baptized, It lieth on the part of <hi>R. B.</hi> if I miſtake not to declare by what right, they being a part ſhould be put by: If he can ſhew no further diſcharge but that Allegorie, they will doe well enough. I told him if a houſhold were tendered to Baptiſme, and I will now put the caſe if hee was to be the Baptizer, and there ſhould be an infant, two or three in it, and <hi>Pauls</hi> example ſhould be alleadged to him; by what warrant would he put them by; or who ſhould be his pattern? It ſeemeth he would rather chuſe to follow the diſciples which Chriſt blamed for hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 14.</note> Children in their comming to him, rather then the minde of our Lord or example of <hi>Paul:</hi> But what I inferred about this he paſſed by with ſilence, And think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to pay me home ſaying, this proveth no more the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of children, then it proveth the baptizing of noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious drunkards, theeves and ſwearers, or whole hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholds have bin baptized in ſom houſholds, there are ſuch, <hi>ergo,</hi> If I ſhould tell <hi>R. B.</hi> that <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> did baptize ſuch, and ſo the cauſe is by him unaware granted, he would <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 7. <hi>Luke.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12.</note> tell mee they confeſſed their ſins firſt, but the ſcripture telleth him and us all, that they were a generation of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, whoſe good fruits were not then brought forth: pleaſing himſelfe in the paralell he ſaith to me, who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:155820:27"/> ſeeth not your folly: I may I ſuppoſe with more ground Retort it on <hi>R. B.</hi> againe for making ſuch a paralell and Illuſion, for would he have drunkards &amp;c. to be baptized whether they would or no? And if theſe being in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily confeſſe their ſinnes, though they forſake them not, ſure <hi>R. B.</hi> (or otherwiſe he differeth from thoſe of his owne way,) eſpecially if they own but totall dipping, will thinke it meet to baptize them, upon that their confeſſion and profeſſion, though they were, and doe after appeare to remaine ſuch drunkards, theeves and whores as hee ſpeaketh of: who may not ſee <hi>R. B.</hi> his ſhallowneſſe thus to pleaſe himſelfe with juſt nothing.</p>
            <p>He commeth to the next, I ſaid the whole Church of <hi>Colloſſe</hi> was baptized as the whole church of old were cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed; now a part of the Church which was thus bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with Chriſt in baptiſme were children. To this hee anſwereth our queſtion is of Infants and not of children in the generall, ſome of which may be old. <hi>R.</hi> B. told me I loved to wrangle, but ſure he is ſore ſicke of the diſeaſe himſelfe. Infants and Children not come to underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I count one and the ſame &amp; I ſuppoſe properly, and of ſuch is our queſtion, ſuch were members of the Church of old &amp; circumciſed; ſuch are members of the church yet ſtill for ought any thing R. B. can ſay to the contrary, the Apoſtle <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. ſpeaking in like manner, ſpeaketh of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants <note place="margin">10. 16.</note> or children not growen in knowledge: ſuch as our Lord tooke in his Armes and ſaid of ſuch were his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>Mark</hi>
               </note> To little purpoſe unleſſe to deceive the ſimple, doth R. B. ſet forth that old perſons, relatively may be called Children. I could alſo ſhew that an infant of a day old hath the like expreſſion. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. But he ſeemeth to have a lame argument, upon which he much relieth, the Apoſtle did not write to infants: I ſay he wrote to the whole and to Children Incluſively; as a part of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:155820:27"/> whole, yea to ſuch as for preſent could make little uſe of what he wrote<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> holy men of old they wrote as they were guided by the ſpirit, in like manner the Apoſtle wrote. Now of old the Law and the prophets, the precepts and promiſe therein were to children incluſively: and ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ene.</hi> 17. 7. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 4. <hi>Deu.</hi> 29. 1</note> in their order, the Covenant to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that by <hi>Moſes</hi> from God it was to young and old: to whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> pertained the adoption and the giving the Law, the ſervice of God and promiſes; yea expreſly Infants that could not expreſſe themſelves verbally, enter Covenant with God, all which minded it will appeare, to be falſe which R. B. ſaith that the apoſtle did not write to Infants. But R. B. muſt have his veine, to take all things in the caſe of children excluſively, which concernes their right in the favours of God, with their Godly Parents. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively he will take Infants with unbeleevers and the wicked of the world, and ſo liable to the ſame wrath, let what will be ſayd to the contrary, though he have not the leaſt ſhew for it out of Gods word: ſo as to end this, If Infants or children not come to knowledge were of the Church, and the whole Church was buried with Chriſt by Baptiſme, then were children Baptized. That they are let what before be minded. Hee concludeth with ſaying, theſe exampies will yeeld little ſatisfaction: To which I ſay and end they will yeeld more then his examples brought for the warrant of an unbaptized perſon Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of others or himſelfe; or for what he alleadged for childrens diſcharge from the Church.</p>
            <p>I ſaid there was a command for the baptiſing children: <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 19. <hi>Goe &amp;c Baptiſe all Nations;</hi> not one onely, as the Nation of the Jewes. I illuſtrated the ſence by paralell reference to other places of <hi>Scripture, God</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of old declared that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould bee a Father of many Nations, all which Nations according to <hi>Chriſts</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:155820:28"/> command muſt be baptiſed, a part whereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are Infants, or Children not come to underſtanding: as Infants were apart of that one Nation of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> It is likely <hi>R. B.</hi> cannot but muſt needs be angry, that I take this place of Scripture to prove that, which hee is ſo much againſt when it was the onely Scripture, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he made to ſerve him at all turnes, and in every caſe about Baptiſme, as before may be obſerved.</p>
            <p>To this he anſwereth thus, <hi>Abraham</hi> indeed was to be a Father of many Nations, ſome whereof hee ſaith were his naturall and carnall ſeed, borne after the fleſh, as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but by the way can <hi>R. B.</hi> put no difference betwixt <hi>Iſhmael</hi> &amp; the <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> and the <hi>Iewes;</hi> If he cannot he ſure hath very ſmall judgement; Theſe he ſaith further for unbeliefe were rejected and caſt off, but he doth not tell us, the Order of it, neither is it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether true, which he ſpeaketh of the cauſe, <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was caſt out firſt, and in him all the <hi>Iſmaelites,</hi> and the cauſe was not unbeliefe, but making, and this which was firſt, was the type of that which followed, the caſting of and rejecting of the <hi>Iewes</hi> for unbeliefe, at that time when <hi>Chriſt</hi> came unto them being his owne, and they received him not, this rejecting of the <hi>Iewes</hi> for unbeliefe R. <hi>B.</hi> denyed, and would not grant, and he thought hee had good reaſon for it, becauſe he thought then in his deep judgement it would imply, as if they had been the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God by nature, and free that way: but now of himſelfe he is pleaſed to acknowledge ſome: further hee ſaith as thoſe were caſt off, ſo the old and carnall Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as before he ſaith, he ſhewed, I then and now again tell him, that was a carnall expreſſion, ſo to call that gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious covenant of Almightie <hi>God: Abraham</hi> hee ſaith had other Nations, which were ſo reputed in regard of their Faith, and walking in his ſteps; I ſay ſurely theſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:155820:28"/> are the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Nations, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. which place he alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, in obſerving to whom <hi>Abraham</hi> was a Father to: and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 19 <hi>Eph.</hi> 16.</note> ſaith marke, and ſo I ſay marke them <hi>Nations</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and walke in the ſteps of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and who ſaith otherwiſe. But to young and old compleat <hi>Nations,</hi> as was the <hi>Nation</hi> of the <hi>Iewes.</hi> He goeth on and ſaith <hi>Gala.</hi> 3. 29. ſuch as are <hi>Chriſts,</hi> are <hi>Abrahams</hi> young Children, are <hi>Chriſt</hi> even as <hi>Iſaac,</hi> of ſuch he ſaith himſelfe, are his Kingdome, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are fellow heires &amp;c. Theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Nations</hi> he meaneth, or elſe he deludeth in the caſe: are <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeed, and are by expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to be baptiſed, <hi>Math.</hi> 28. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. hath not the man travelled farre to little purpoſe: unleſſe to confute himſelfe: The <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that beleeve, they are <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeed, and are by <hi>Chriſts</hi> expreſſe command to be baptiſed, as <hi>R. B.</hi> acknowledgeth, and Infants are a part of theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> and ſo alſo to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed. But what ſaith hee? is all this to the baptiſing of Children that beleeve not? I aske how hee knoweth they doe not believe, if they believe not they cannot be ſaved: he againe ſaith, and therefore not believing are none of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeed, <hi>Iſaack</hi> when a Infant could not beleeve after that way <hi>R. B.</hi> intendeth, yet he was <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeed, ſo were the Infants of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, and now we <hi>Gentiles</hi> are as <hi>Iſaack,</hi> ſo as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it is much to the purpoſe, though he ſee it not: and therefore ſayes that children not believing, are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none of ABRAHAMS ſpirituall ſeed, who onely are to bee baptiſed, fie what poore matter is this; hee ſaith that which followeth is likewiſe nothing to the purpoſe, namely that the <hi>Nations</hi> that are made ABRAHAMS ſeed, the NATIONS that are ſaved, the Kingdomes that ſhall become the Kingdomes of the Lord, muſt needs receive <hi>Chriſts</hi> badg,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:155820:29"/> and be baptiſed, this he ſaith is granted but proveth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; that is a wonderfull thing if Children bee apart as before of thoſe <hi>Nations,</hi> that he ſhould grant the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing of the whole, and yet denie one part; what is his reaſon that before, over againe, none are <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, but ſuch as are <hi>Chriſts,</hi> firſt <hi>Iſaack</hi> and the Infants of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> were firſt <hi>Chriſts,</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are partakers of the ſame promiſe: But he urgeth further (like an unwiſe man) they walke in his ſteps, what did <hi>Jſaack</hi> ſo walke when he was an Infant? doe his workes? to apply theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to Infants ſheweth great weakneſſe and folly: yet he goeth on farther, and ſaith that no Kingdome doth become the Kingdome of the Lord, but thoſe that feare and ſerve him <hi>kiſſe the Sonne, Pſal.</hi> 101. <hi>Heare his voyce Acts</hi> 3. 22. and have him to reigne over them, all which he applyeth againſt Children, groſſely abuſing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as any man that hath but halfe an eye may ſee: I <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x.</hi> 19. 6</note> aske him did the <hi>Nation</hi> of the <hi>Jewes</hi> that was <hi>Gods Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> as well as <hi>Abrahams,</hi> and a peculiar people, their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants and all doe ſo? did thoſe Infants ſo heare <hi>Gods</hi> voyce, ſeare and ſerve <hi>God</hi> kiſſe the Son; <hi>R. B.</hi> is in a Labyrinth ſure. But yet further he urgeth that the Scriptures doe, not declare the ſalvation of any; but ſuch as doe believe, ſo no children in his account, but his reckoning is utterly untrue: he goeth on, ſaying thoſe that believe on the Sonne have life, but ſuch as believe not (as Children hee ſaith doe not) the wrath of <hi>God</hi> abideth on them, a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 2 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> doom for Children, <hi>Herod</hi> was a great Enemy to the Children of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> for he deſtroyed them all in one day, R. B. exceedeth he deſigneth all the children in the children in the world at once to utter deſtruction and the wrath of God; he concludeth thus, therefore in refuſing Infants which beleeve no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but have as before the wrath of God abiding on them. A fearefull doctrine, R. B. ſaith
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:155820:29"/> for himſelf and the reſt with him, if any pleaſe to beleeve him that they doe not curtaile the Nations which <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was to be a father of. If any will take his word for it they may; but beleeve him who liſt, I ſhall not, for as <hi>Herod</hi> did curtaile, that is cut off a part of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> when he deſtroyed the children of two yeeres, for which there was ſo great mourning in <hi>Ramah,</hi> and as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile <hi>Iſrael</hi> when he deſtroyed or did endeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.</note> their children: So in like manner to reject children from a nation or people in a relative way as <hi>R. B.</hi> doth, is to curtaile a nation or people what ever <hi>R. B.</hi> ſay to the contrary. When God changed his purpoſe of deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Nineve,</hi> he ſpeaketh of the greatneſſe of the people, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iona.</hi> 4. 11.</note> and that there were ſixſcore thouſand that could not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne betwixt the right han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and the left, that is chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, a part of the whole, that muſt be either be ſaved or periſh together in the judgement: The infants of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were a part of the nation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and ſuch as ſhared both in mercies and judgements, which happily when <hi>R. B.</hi> hath better conſidered of hee may change alſo his thoughts about children and have more charitie toward them. I ſhall ſet downe the Argument againe, and leave the reader to judge of it, now he hath heard what is ſaid of both ſides. There is a command for baptizing of nations; Children or infants are a part of theſe nations, <hi>Ergo</hi> there is the command of Chriſt for Baptizing infants. But R. <hi>B.</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> angrie about this 28. <hi>Matth.</hi> being alleadged againſt him, and ſaith, nothing can be ſaid more contrarie poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, for what it is alleadged, ſo ſenſuring me for vain jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and one that underſtood not what I ſpoke nor where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I did affirme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he concludeth his anſwer, never ſaying any thing to that of the Iewiſh Nation being borne again in one day, whether then their infants ſhall be left cut is no more capable of the Grace of God, nor yet to what I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:155820:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:155820:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:155820:31"/> further ſaid about their being firſt taught &amp; then baptized which I ſaid was an adition of their owne coine, not found in the ſcripture, and being preſumption in any to adde it to the 28. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. I ſaid in the end of my diſcourſe alſo that diſtinction is to be put betwixt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of yeeres and infants, that perſons of yeeres are firſt to be taught, but not children, as of old the <hi>Proſelites</hi> were, but not their infants. That it were unreaſonable to require it of them now in Baptiſme, it not being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them in Circumciſion, that no Conditionall if, can be put in the caſe of infants. To all which <hi>R. B.</hi> ſaith nothing, for ſure he granteth it all, and ſo taketh himſelfe guiltie of that frowardneſſe I obſerved in ſome, in ſetting children againſt their parents in the caſe of beleeving and intereſt in the Covenant of Almightie God: a thing they have taken up by tradition, and never learned it of the holy ſcripture: And yet in it lieth the great force and ſtrength of theſe mens reaſoning, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing young children to their godly Parents, making the one a beleever and the other an Infidell, making the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant of a beleever an unbeleever, to whom pertaineth the wrath of God, and ſo applying and opening all ſcriptures for the one againſt the other, when as it is verie cleare by the ſcripture, as in part may be ſeene by what is before declared. That children are alwayes taken and minded as included, and ſo ſharing and having right with their Parents and not otherwiſe. I ſhall beare his cenſure pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently which he layeth on me, and conclude this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, ſaying as <hi>R. B.</hi> doth, and I thinke the reader will judge I ſay the truth; that <hi>R. B.</hi> his whole Anſwer is not onely weake and Impertinent, but that it doth declare the Authour thereof to be very erroneous, that it is full of fayned fables fathered unjuſtly on his oppoſite, and hath many things in it contradictorie to his owne prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:155820:31"/> ſo as he that ſhall read the Anſwer diſcovered and laid open, will ſure judge what ever <hi>R. B.</hi> intended hee hath rendered his cauſe and practiſe which hee endeavoured to defend, evill and naught, and an error to be deſerted and ſhunned of all the people of God, which God give them wiſdome to ſee aright.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reply">
            <head>A ſhort reply, to the frivolous exceptions of <hi>E.</hi> B.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ee being deſirous to vent and put off his notions, though verie raw and undigeſted as may eaſily be ſeene, and meeting with my diſcourſe, he thought good to have a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing at it though to little purpoſe God knoweth, as is the reſt of the matter of his booke, to which he doth adde this ſhort and haſtie Anſwer. I ſhall rather chuſe that he ſhall pleaſe himſelfe with the great ſtrength of his matter, and the utter inabillitie that is in any to Anſwer: rather then trouble my ſelfe in endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to ſhew the deceitfulneſſe of his wares, and ſo hurt his market: he having ſo great a deſire to put them off: I ſuppoſe any indifferent Chapman can ſee into it. I ſhall onely make a ſhort reply to what is excepted againſt in my diſcourſe. Firſt he excepteth againſt this that Chriſt ſhould be ſaid to be a widower if his viſible Church died, and ceaſed to be any more in the world; to this I have anſwered before and referre the reader to it: Chriſt the husband of his Church muſt be a Widow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:155820:32"/> if his Church died; To this hee ſayth wee differ not in the matter or ſubſtance: No that is ſtrange, what is his reaſon? He ſaith the Church is either in heaven or earth, ſo I ſay is a mans wife when ſhe is dead, either in the world or out of it: But hee ſaith Chriſt hath a Church though no viſible one, but our queſtion is of the viſible, that is Chriſts wife <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. If that die or died, Chriſt muſt be a widower ſure. But he ſaith his Church became Inviſible; then it changed the nature of it. But he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it is cleare, that ſome time it was ſo inviſible <hi>Reve.</hi> 6. 13. 14. but ſure he wanteth a cleare judgement as in other things ſo in this Scripture, heaven departed away as a ſcrole when it is rolled together, A ſcrole is a viſible ſubſtance when it is rolled up, though not ſo viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as when unrolled, heaven the eſtate of Chriſt Church departed away no otherwiſe then as a ſcrole, which is the ſame and continueth it being rolled as unrolled, indeed he is viſible rolled, more viſible unrolled, <hi>R. B.</hi> his infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, namely that the Church is not alway viſible is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound: Till the eight ſeale was powred forth Heaven or the Church was as a ſcrole unrolled, ſo as the things therein written might be ſeene: ſo was the Church while it remained now pure: But after that time it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted as a ſcrole rolled up, ſo was the caſe, and in ſome ſort is ſtill of the Church under deepe defection; The reſtoring of the Church to puritie is the unrolling of the ſcrole, begun and yet a doing: he addeth but to what purpoſe I ſuppoſe he knoweth not <hi>Reve.</hi> 11. 7. 12.</p>
            <p>Further he ſaith the Church was hid in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for a time, and times and halfe a time: But from whom is it that ſhe was thus hid? from the Serpen I but if ſhe be hid ſhe is preſerved and hath her being, and having a being ſhe is viſible: nothing can be more plaine She is hid from the rage of the ſerpent from the crueltie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:155820:32"/> of the enemie, but viſible to her friends, and to the members and thoſe that in good will doe ſeeke her. If <hi>E. B.</hi> in ſome danger of the enemie, as in the time of the Biſhops ſhould have retired to ſome place of ſecreſie and there have hid himſelfe, was he therefore to his wife and other friends a man inviſible, becauſe ſo hid. Truely any man of reaſon may ſee to what purpoſe theſe Scriptures ſerve his turne, and that they are fully againſt him and his opinion which he bringeth them for, and do prove the continuedneſſe of the Church and viſibillitie of it which he oppoſeth: In the wilderneſſe the Church continued, if by wilderneſſe hee will not underſtand the ſtate of defection, he muſt then underſtand by wilderneſſe private places, for other ſence I ſuppoſe he cannot finde I he chooſe the latter as I ſuppoſe he will: If he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or would take paines to traverſe the world, If he could not finde the Church remaining in <hi>Europe,</hi> in <hi>Aſia, Affrica, or America</hi> he might finde her, for in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhe is to be preſerved as before: and there finding of her he might have lighted his candle, and beene bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized and added to the Church. And he ſhould not have beene put upon ſuch a neceſſitie as to begin Baptiſme by an unbaptized perſon acting of it without any Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or warrant from Chriſt: But hee and others of his minde had rather ſpare his paines and labour of ſeeking and ſearching the wilderneſſe for her, and without Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or word of God, beleeve and hold ſhe is ſeaſed out of the world and gone to heaven, and muſt be ſo raiſed and reſtored in the earth againe, by this way of their own deviſing, which never came into the minde of Almightie God.</p>
            <p>His ſecond exception is to what I propounded, that if <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. 31.</note> Baptiſme was loſt and fallen out of the world none but a Chriſt, a <hi>Moſes, an Elias</hi> or at leaſt a prophet from heaven
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:155820:33"/> might reſtore, the blinde <hi>Jewes</hi> could ſee this that it was unlawfull for any other: To this hee ſayth that he gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that an ordinance loſt and fallen out of the world none but a Chriſt a <hi>Moſes Elias</hi> or a prophet from heaven can raiſe it: Baptiſme: was thus loſt hee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, when did Chriſt, <hi>Moſes, Elias,</hi> or any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet from Heaven, come to raiſe it againe? where are they, or who be they that we may doe them reverence? Sure he can ſhew none ſuch; But this hee rhinketh may ſerve, beleevers having Chriſt the Word and Spirit, ſo he ſayth may doe it. Indeed they that have <hi>Chriſt, Moſes, Elias,</hi> or prophets from heaven may doe great things: but alas theſe being in heaven, are not at their beck. It is likely he meaneth they have their word, there was never any held any error ſo great but did aſſume to have that and the Spirit alſo: But ſuppoſing to have Chriſt the Word and Spirit: how then doth he prove ſuch may raiſe a loſt ordinance without ſpeciall Commiſſion: he quoteth foure Scriptures <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 19. 20. 11. 11. <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 6. We will view the Scriptures. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 19. 20. If two of you agree, and againe, where two or three are gathered in my Name &amp;c. To which I ſay that it is not meant two or three unbaptized perſons ſuch have no warrant Commiſſion or promiſe in this kinde; <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his family and friends were two three ſuch: yet they muſt ſend for <hi>Peter;</hi> Two or three is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 2. 5. <hi>Ast.</hi> 2. 41.</note> or uſually and I judge truely, taken for the Church; two or three unbaptiſed perſons, I deny to be a Church; let <hi>E. B.</hi> that would have an example of baptiſing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, ſhew an example, or any ground from Scripture of a unbaptiſed Church, There is cleare examples of Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers being Baptized and added to the Church, where there was a Miniſtrie of Chriſt: however where there were Baptized perſons to Baptize them, but alas for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:155820:33"/> beleevers ſo called to become a Church, being unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized is without all warrant of ſcripture I conceive I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot neede to wade further in anſwer, for doubtleſſe this Scripture will be judged by the reader to bee imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to his purpoſe. The 11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>Luke</hi> 7. 28. both which containe one matter are the next: They ſpeake of John and that the leaſt in the Kingdome of God is greater then he: though he were great indeed. The force is ſupoſed to lie here, greater, and ſo may baptize as hee did, without Warrant or Commiſſion, though he had one. By this reaſon women may baptize, they being of the kingdome of Heaven and beleevers, but ſure unbaptized perſons cannot be the Kingdome of Heaven in this ſence: <hi>Cornelius</hi> might have baptized his family and friends, and needed not to have ſent for <hi>Peter.</hi> Certainly our Lord was greater then <hi>John,</hi> and the Lord of all beleevers, yet he did not baptize himſelfe or others, but went to <hi>John,</hi> that he might fullfill righteouſneſſe, and ſo would theſe, were they like minded to him, they would goe to them that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 15.</note> were baptized, and had Commiſſion to baptize others: Theſe Scriptures the ſtrength whereof lieth in a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive way, without all queſtion E. <hi>B.</hi> doth not yet under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſcope of them, and that it maketh nothing for him, every ordinary judgement will ſee, and I will ſay no more.</p>
            <p>The 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 7. 8. is the laſt place by which he will prove that unbaptized perſons beleeving may baptize others, and ſo raiſe the ordinance loſt and fallen out of the world, this place of the Apoſtle is that of <hi>Moſes Deu.</hi> 30. 11. 12. 13. 14. <note place="margin">1 <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 13. 9. 11. 2. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hron.</hi> 26. 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 33. 40</note> It would better have fitted <hi>Saul</hi> to have excuſed his diſobedience he being in a great ſtrait, and fooliſhly adventuring to ſacrifice, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> the king might better and to more purpoſe have alleadged the ſame for burning incenſe, for which the prieſt withſtood him hee
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:155820:34"/> being for it ſmitten with leproſie. Can E. B. account God to be the God of order, or thinke well of him for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a breach in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi> for neglect of order? and hold th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> every beleever may without any more adoe, act any ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of never ſo high a nature or peculiar concernment? and ſaying, ſay not who ſhall a ſcend into Heaven, and the word is neare them, will ſerve their turne and bear them out, Alas it would not ſerve <hi>Saul</hi> nor <hi>Vzza</hi> nor <hi>Vzziah</hi> though a King, neither will it in the leaſt ſerve an unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized perſon; the which I leave alſo to the judgement of the Reader. After this he ſpeaketh that the Scripture is ſilent of <hi>John</hi> his baptizing of himſelfe; I ſay though it be, yet it is not ſilent concerning his Commiſſion, they ſhew theſe it were to purpoſe. Then abruptly he falleth could on the Apoſtacie of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>AntiChriſt</hi> &amp; ſaith the Apoſtacy of Anti-Chriſt, greater then i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that of Iſrael, indeed ſo it had need, with reference to their courſe, and ſo he ſaith though they did not againe circumciſe themſelves, yet now they may againe be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, though the Scripture be as ſilent concerning it as it is of <hi>Johns</hi> Baptizing himſelfe &amp;c. It is well he will inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly acknowledge the ſilence of the Scripture in the matter: but what is their courſe now not having the Scripture for the rule of it, a voluntarie courſe of their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 8.</note> owne deviſing to be ſhunned of all Gods people, who are to cleave to the Law and Teſtimonie: But we will a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle minde his reaſon, why the Apoſtacie of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is greater then that of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> it is this, they were called <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> and <hi>Egyptians,</hi> theſe were the worſt of <hi>Pagans</hi> and ſo of the <hi>Gentiles Reve.</hi> 11. 2. 8. It is but Spiritually they are ſo called: And <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their Apoſtacie from God is called by the like termes <hi>Eſay</hi> 1. 10. 57. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 3. Neither doth it appeare that <hi>Sodomites</hi> and <hi>Egyptians</hi> were the worſt of Heathen, unleſſe any pleaſe to beleeve his bare
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:155820:34"/> ſaying ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> truely this is a poor way of confuting a matter.</p>
            <p>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> further ſaith <hi>Iſraels</hi> Apoſtacie did not raze the foundation of the conſtitution of their Church: It is well he ſo holdeth, others of his way have not held ſo; <hi>Iſrael</hi> forſooke God and his pure worſhip and followed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4 17. 8. 4.</note> Idols, They worſhipped the Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> if their ground were true, that corruption it maketh a nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, it is marvellous they ſhould remaine a true Church.</p>
            <p>But it is plaine he ſaith that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> hath changed all ordinances, both in Church and Miniſtery, Worſhip and Government: <hi>Eſai</hi> 24. 5. and ſo hath deſtroyed bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. To which I anſwer, it is not ſo plaine as it is plaine: E. <hi>B.</hi> is fooliſhly confident of his owne opinions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, though he have no ground for them: doth the 24. <hi>Eſay</hi> 5. prove it ſo plainly? E. <hi>B.</hi> hath a veine to make any thing prove his matter; he thinketh he hath to deale with children, with whom he is ſo out of charitie: hee goeth on adding one thing to another without any rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo ſaith the matter of the Church under the Goſpell muſt know the Lord and bee all taught of him. If all of E. <hi>B.</hi> his Church doe ſo know God, and be ſo taught of him it is well; if it be ſo, they have the more wrong done them: further he bringeth all the difference betwixt him &amp; the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> to a very narrow point, and that is they do not <hi>baptiſe</hi> believers on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſing faith and ſins &amp;c. If they did, they would not leave her; they doe baptize perſons of yeeres in <hi>Nova Spania</hi> and other parts of the <hi>Indies;</hi> yea in <hi>Rome</hi> and ſo alſo in <hi>England</hi> they baptize <hi>Iewes, Turks</hi> and <hi>Moors,</hi> who confeſſe their faith and their ſins: they baptize infants alſo that is a leſſe errour then the worſhipping of the Calves which when <hi>E. B.</hi> hath well conſidered, happily he may leave off his ſeparation and be reconciled againe.</p>
            <p>Further he ſeemeth to ſay ſomething to what I minded in my diſcourſe that ſome are ſo filled with prejudice,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:155820:35"/> that they have no patience to think of the church eſtate: remaining under <hi>Antichriſt</hi> exaltation: to this he ſaith they ſhall ever bee ready to ſpeake or write; I ſay like enough ſo, but not to heare it ſeemeth. It is a vertue to be ſwift to heare and ſlow to ſpeake: I did in my diſcourſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 1. 19.</note> deſire any to ſet forth the hurt that commeth of holding the Ordinance of the Church and Baptiſme, to have bin in captivitie in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and there preſerved by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, for a time &amp;c. And now by the ſame power brought forth to freedome and puritie, God returning to build his Tabernacle broke downe and ruined: But <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</note> not deſtroyed, as ſometime of old the Church and veſſels of the Lord were in <hi>Babylon</hi> and thence returned: to the veſſels he anſwereth, but to the Church it ſeemeth hee knew not what to anſwer, and ſo paſſeth it by with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, notwithſtanding he hold as before, as in the end of his third replie, the conſtitution of that Church was founded in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and being removed thence by his ground muſt become voide. To the veſſels he moſt ignorantly replieth and ſaith, the veſſels of the Lords houſe had no relation to the ſprinkling of infants; his reaſon is, they were the Lords ordinances, and is not the Church and Baptiſme ſo alſo? he ſaith they needed no new caſting ſo long as they remained the ſame, ſo the Church and Baptiſme neede no new raiſing, they remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame: But he conclude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the ſprinkling of infants was never Gods Ordinance; indeed if hee were a Chriſt, a <hi>Moſes, Eltas</hi> or prophet from heaven, his bare affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might paſſe and be taken for good, but it is well wee neede not beleeve him unleſſe wee will: So hee ſaith the Argument is to no purpoſe: hee might well ſay ſo of his ſimple anſwer he pleaſeth himſelf withall. He propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a caſe I ſhal not trouble my ſelf, to take away the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hee hath in it, being aſſured any one that hath reaſon
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:155820:35"/> in him will ſee it is but a fancie. Another exception is to a paſſage in my diſcourſe, wherin I ſaid it was marvellous they had not patience about raiſing Baptiſme loſt, ſeeing ſome of them expect Chriſt perſonally to appeare, in the world againe. I ſaid happily he might bee angrie at their ſuddaine attempt that they did not ſtay his comming, or at leaſt till hee had given them Commiſſion as hee did <hi>John</hi> to prepare his way before him; this he ſetteth downe corruptly, &amp; ſayth I ſay ſome hold Chriſt is to come and raigne at <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> He ſayth I ſay I would have had them ſtay til then for the ordinance: I ſaid only I marvelled they had not patience to ſtay: I ſhall beare his charges and take notice of his anſwer; If the want of the viſibilitie of the Church maketh Chriſt a widower<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Church <hi>P. B.</hi> is a Member of, was unheard of till within theſe two hundred yeeres, this he learned of the Papiſt, where was your Church before <hi>Luther?</hi> well two hundred yeeres is ſome Antiquitie, more then two or three yeeres, ſuch as is the deſcent of the totall dippers in this Kingdome: hee fooliſhly concludeth ſo Chriſt a widower till then. But he might know, that though the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches came then out of Bondage and Corruption, to free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and puritie, yet there might be other Churches in <hi>Aſia</hi> or in <hi>Affrica,</hi> though there remained none, but ſo corrupt in <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo as Chriſt ſhould not need to bee a widower for want of ſuch a viſible Church as <hi>P. B.</hi> is of, being but of two hundred yeeres ſtanding: But the afor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid inference he maketh with a promiſe, and that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I hold the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> a true Church; I hold not the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> a true Church nor never did: but this I hold, that the Church eſtate remained in or under the <hi>Romane</hi> deffection, the man of ſin ſitting in the Temple of God: ſo as Chriſt was not widower, though his Church was polluted and defiled kept under and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:155820:36"/> as it fared in like caſe with the ſpouſe of Chriſt the Church, when ſhe went a whoring from him and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23. 17. 30 14. 11. 26. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 13.</note> her ſelfe, and had other Lords to reigne over her: At length he turnes his confutation into a quaere, and ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how I dare ſeparate from her; how durſt he ſeparate from the Church he was left a Member of, for which hee was dealt withall by them; he may reſolve the caſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: But for ſatisfaction to others in this matter, I ſhall give ſome account: Chriſtianitie and the eſtate of the Church I hold remained under the great defection of the man of ſin; God in time called out his people <hi>Reve.</hi> 18. 4. The <hi>Waldenſes</hi> firſt the Reformed Churches in <hi>France, Germany, Belgia,</hi> then came forth into freedome and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in obedience to that call, and ſerved God apart, as ſometimes the Chriſtians did leave the Church of the <hi>Jewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Babylon</hi> is Gods people, yea his people in Covenant, theſe words <hi>Reve.</hi> 4. 18. being the words of the Covenant <hi>Iere.</hi> 31. So as the matter of the Church remaining, is clearely gathered from thence, none being the people of God in Covenant ſo, but onely thoſe of his Church, the Church eſtate and ordinances in ſome conſideration there remaining, they comming out of her: to wit Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, they muſt come out of, and ſeparate from the Church ſo either remayning ſo farre as concernes Member-ſhip: So as I might anſwer we ſepara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e from her, becauſe we are ſo bidden by Almighty God, though in ſome ſence the Church be there remayning: And if E. B. or any other would pleaſe but to minde M. <hi>Iunius,</hi> and <hi>Duple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis Lord of Mornay,</hi> as they doe M. <hi>Rogers</hi> they might learne this, at leaſt they might ſee that ſuch an opinion is neither ſingular nor new: to further his daring queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on touching ſeparation, I ſay ſeparation is totall. For it is in part: E. B. profeſſeth totall ſeparation from <hi>Rome</hi> and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:155820:36"/> 
               <hi>England</hi> which he accounteth on: but he is nothing true to his principle, for all hee caſteth away the Baptiſme he received there; for why by like reaſon doth hee not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the ſame Saviour and Redeemer <hi>Jeſus</hi> profeſſed by them? why doth hee not renounce the Scriptures by them maintained? eſpecially the Tranſlation of them, this being an outward thing as is Baptiſme? why holdeth he with them the doctrine of the Trinitie the two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Chriſt in one perſon? why obſerveth he with them the Lords day and retaineth their Marriages, and ſubmitteth to Magiſtracie and government there? ſure the man is partiall; he practiſeth but ſeparation in part, though he profeſſe totall, he commeth much ſhort of his owne principle; and it is well he doth, for ſurely he ought but to ſeparate in part from the evill of a perſon or thing, and ſo from the evils there: for ſo it is ſaid, that ye partake not of her ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, but of the vertues or good there; or in any what ever we may and ought, and it is as great an evill to ſeparate from good that being of God, as it is not to ſeparate from evill and ſin.</p>
            <p>But he hath another daring quaere, how dare they ſet up a ſtate before Chriſt come? They (the reformed Churches he meaneth) that are, he ſaith, but of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres ſtanding. To which I ſay it is likely they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no ſuch perſonall comming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And further I ſay if he pleaſe to looke into the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their Confeſſions they will informe him, and tell him the ground of their practice, not onely in forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Babylon</hi> and comming out of the Church in deepe defection: But alſo of their Congregating together and worſhipping of God purely according to his word; And this not by way of new beginning either in regard of matter or form, but by way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reforming themſelves, being Chriſtians, or baptized beleevers and ſo matter; and alſo
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:155820:37"/> there Congregated in regard of forme, though in deepe defection, and in a verie corrupt condition: ſo as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of matter or forme, there was no need of our Lord Chriſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Elias,</hi> or a prophet from heaven perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to appeare about the matter, for at the moſt they being baptized Chriſtians: It is but a multiplying of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, which is ſure lawfull and ever was, and E. <hi>B.</hi> will not be againſt it. The whole anſwer to this daring quaere is but according to the injunction of the Apoſtle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the defection. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 22. 15. Stand faſt and keep the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions yea have beene taught by word or Epiſtle: the reſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his exceptions I have replied unto in anſwere to <hi>R. B</hi> and ſo ſhall not trouble my ſelfe nor the Reader about them, but ſhall referre the whole matter to the cenſure of the Godly-wiſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 1. <hi>L.</hi> 11. for the. <hi>r.</hi> he <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 9. for is ſaid. <hi>r.</hi> I ſaid. <hi>l</hi> 16. for where <hi>r.</hi> wherefore. <hi>l.</hi> 25. put out apart. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 7. for ſo before. <hi>r.</hi> ſee before. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> 5. adde to where might. he might, <hi>p.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>l.</hi> 33. for deection <hi>r.</hi> defection. <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 1. for R. B. <hi>r.</hi> P. B. <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 19. put out. <hi>r.</hi> no <hi>p.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>l.</hi> 33. for my. <hi>r.</hi> the <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 33. for neither <hi>r.</hi> whither. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 4. adde on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 7. for matter. <hi>r.</hi> water. <hi>l.</hi> 33. to made adde voide. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 30. make a ſtop at the end of notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 6. for our <hi>r.</hi> out. <hi>l.</hi> 21. for written. <hi>r.</hi> write. <hi>p.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 9. for that is. <hi>r.</hi> that dipping is. <hi>p.</hi> 28. <hi>l.</hi> 28. the end. 29. the beginning for all caſes. <hi>r.</hi> a caſe. <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>l.</hi> 22. for dipping <hi>r.</hi> dip. p. 30. <hi>l.</hi> 8. for R. B. were. <hi>r.</hi> R. <hi>B.</hi> way. <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>l.</hi> 9. for ſlipping. <hi>r.</hi> skipping. <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>l.</hi> 5. for but ſomething. <hi>r.</hi> but at ſomething. <hi>p.</hi> 33. l. 6. put out. our blood. <hi>l.</hi> 11. for ſome <hi>r.</hi> ſonne. <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>l.</hi> 14. for common. <hi>r.</hi> come upon. <hi>p.</hi> 41. <hi>l.</hi> 19. for nature conſidered, <hi>r.</hi> by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſidered <hi>p.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>l.</hi> 27. for or <hi>r.</hi> for <hi>p.</hi> 48. <hi>l.</hi> 19. for making <hi>r.</hi> mocking. <hi>l.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>r.</hi> the ſame. <hi>p.</hi> 50 <hi>l.</hi> 31. leave out children in the <hi>p</hi> 51. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> for it. <hi>l.</hi> 29 for and in. <hi>r.</hi> and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Courteous Reader paſſe by the eſcapes in correcting, and amend them with thy pen if thou pleaſe, Take notice that there is ſome miſtakes in ſtops, and the quotations in the Margent are not placed even.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
